<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian memorandum, or advertisement wherein is handled the doctrine of reproofe What it is, how we must reproue, how necessary it is: with exhortations and arguments moving vs to the right performance of that duty, and reproofe for neglecting reproofe. By Richard Truman Mr of Arts and minister of Gods word at Dallington neere Northampton.</title>
            <author>Truman, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13981)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1119:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian memorandum, or advertisement wherein is handled the doctrine of reproofe What it is, how we must reproue, how necessary it is: with exhortations and arguments moving vs to the right performance of that duty, and reproofe for neglecting reproofe. By Richard Truman Mr of Arts and minister of Gods word at Dallington neere Northampton.</title>
                  <author>Truman, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 125, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Lichfield, printer to the Universitie, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Tygres Head by Henry Seale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:1"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A</hi> CHRISTIAN <hi>Memorandum,</hi> OR <hi>Advertiſement wherein is</hi> handled the Doctrine <hi>of Reproofe.</hi> WHAT IT IS, HOW WE MVST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, How neceſſary it is: With Exhortations and Arguments moving vs to the right performance of that duty, and Reproofe for neglecting <hi>Reproofe.</hi> By RICHARD TRVMAN <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts and Miniſter of Gods word at</hi> Dallington <hi>neere</hi> Northampton.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>EPH. 5. 11.</bibl>
               <p>Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe but rather reproue them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Vniverſitie, and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls Church-yard</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Tygres Head</hi> by <hi>Henry Seale.</hi> 1629.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Spencer <hi>Knight of the</hi> Bath, <hi>&amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of</hi> Wormeleighton, <hi>all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward happineſſe, with peace of conſcience in this life, &amp; everlaſting ſaluation in the World to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> It is a true &amp; <note place="margin">Ingenui pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotis eſt fateri per quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us, &amp; haec quaſimere as authoris. Plin</note> ancient ſaying, It is the property of an honeſt and ingenuous minde, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge by whom we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued profite, &amp; this is as it were a reward to the author. Now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bookes and writings are the
<pb facs="tcp:2806:3"/> greateſt riches we haue, being the iſſue and ofſpring of our beſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and deareſt endeauours; I could not but preſent to you the firſt fruits of that tree whoſe plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was cauſed by your owne hand; and the rather that I may giue ſome poore pledge and obui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous teſtimony of my thankfull commemoration &amp; acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch fauours as haue bin on my part receiued from that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonage who is now gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Fathers, as alſo for that fauour and countenance which ſtill I receiue from your ſelfe. I will not ſpeake much of him whoſe owne workes haue giuen teſtimony enough to the world, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2806:3"/> added as to your Honour, ſo to your comfort: yet to free my ſelfe from the aſpertion of <note place="margin">Dixeris male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta cuncta, cum ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cris.</note> vnthankfulneſſe which is a ſinne of ſinnes, and all the evills a man can speake of, I muſt needs ſay ſomething of him, for the conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and fidelity of whoſe loue, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſtill daily comfort: leaſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the world might ſay of mee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that inſcription which <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> cauſed to bee ſet vpon his Tombe when hee had done many fauours for <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; afterwards was baniſht by them. <note place="margin">Ingrata Patria, ne offa qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mea ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. Val. Max.</note> Vnthankfull countrey that haſt not ſo much as my bones. Yea the world can teſtifie how profitable he hath beene to Church &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, who from a louing
<pb facs="tcp:2806:4"/> and noble ambition tooke alwaies pleaſure and delight to be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to ſuch as ſtood in need of him; and that not after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our ignoble benefactors in theſe daies, who profeſſe charity, in meane time the obiect dies, and this is to ſet a diſh of meat vpon a dead mans graue; or elſe they doe good when they themſelues are departed, which howſoeuer it may comfort the liuing yet addes no ioy to him that gaue it being dead; good workes being done after death wee carry the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne behinde vs, it may guide and comfort the followers, but we ſee not what wee doe our ſelues: but good workes done in our life
<pb facs="tcp:2806:4"/> time, is to carry the Lanthorne before vs, whereby we adminiſter helpe to others, and to our owne comfort behold it our ſelues. It ſhall ſuffice to speake but in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; for ſhould I proceed to the commendation of his particular vertues, I preſume I ſhould be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered as he that ſpent a long O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in praiſe of <hi>Hercules, Quis vituperauit?</hi> Who diſpraiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Hercules?</hi> Yet I could not but breake his boxe of ſpikenard wherein his good name was enbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the perfume and ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof might ſomewhat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part itſelfe to the world, conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſpeech of him as <hi>Philip of Hipparchus,</hi> hee died ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <note place="margin">Sibi mature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mihi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2806:5"/> for himſelfe but to mee too ſoone: Let mee therefore returne vnto you moſt <hi>Noble Lord</hi> bearing the character &amp; impreſſe of all his worthy partes, as though they came by ſucceſſion and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, beſeeching you to accept theſe my poore labours, though they be nothing equiualent to that maine debt I owe vnto you. Your acceptance I craue eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know in this world and <hi>Babel</hi> of diſtraction and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of diuided mindes no man can pleaſe all, but ſome will preſume to taxe the whole world: but this ſhall be my comfort, that I haue euer found the beſt learned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, the moſt modest and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:2806:5"/> cenſurers of others: for which cauſe, I was moued and embolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſhelter my ſelfe vnder your religious and iuditious protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which may be to mee like the buckler of <hi>Aiax,</hi> to ſheild me from the detraction of many. And as <hi>Antimachus</hi> being forſaken of all his auditors, proceeded in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his booke, becauſe <hi>Plato</hi> was left, eſteeming him to ouer value them all: ſo if many ſhall diſdaine, and reiect my labours, yet if it pleaſe you to approue &amp; like them, it ſhall administer comfort and encouragement to me: as for ſuch as want both learning and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to iudge aright, or to iudge in loue, I paſse not, if they vſe the
<pb facs="tcp:2806:6"/> freedome of their owne natiue iudgements, &amp; I will reſolue as in the Tragedie, as I haue little hope to obtaine their fauour ſo care I little for their frowne, envy may diſdaine, draw bloode it cannot. Thus being as confident of your fauour, as I am certaine of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of the most, I leaue you and all yours to the bleſſed and proſperous protection of the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhipps euer to command in the Lord <hi>Richard Truman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, It was the ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt Prince that ever raigned. <hi>Withhold not good from them to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 23.</note> 
               <hi>whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to doe it;</hi> and them I take to bee the owners of any good, that ſtand in need of the ſame; few or none there be, to whom direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may not bee profitable in their demeanure, but to ſome more then to others; therefore as the <hi>Almanacks</hi> of <hi>Prognoſticators</hi> are written eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the climate wherein they dwell, ſo my publiſhing this diſcourſe is, chiefly for my owne countries ſake: for amongſt the manifold cauſes of the augmentation and increaſe of ſin
<pb facs="tcp:2806:7"/> though it he not ſo ſeriouſly adviſed and thought vpon, yet doubtleſſe the want of diſcountenancing and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſinne, is one reaſon, why it flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth ſo much in the moſt: and in regard there is one kinde of people, who offend by connivency and ſilence when they ſee ſin committed. I haue endeavoured to put ſome life &amp; zeal into them, by ſtirring them vp to this duty: alſo beholding on the other ſide a strange extreame, namely a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of people too induſtrious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous in reprouing others, who are rough and tetricall ſpirits, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not in every point as preciſe as themſelues, they account them as dogs and ſwine, men of vncleane and prophane diſpoſitions, vnworthy any account or countenance; yet theſe men for want of wiſdome &amp; diſcretion in their behaviour, doe more miſchiefe through a raſh vnadviſedneſſe and want of gouerment then they can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by reprehenſions; therefore I
<pb facs="tcp:2806:7"/> haue performed the beſt I can, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 14. 14.</note> like <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle, out of theſe devourers and <hi>Lyons,</hi> I might bring forth that which may be for meat &amp; ſweetneſse in the diſcovery of this point. Wherein I haue laid downe 1. What it is to reproue ſin. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>,</hi> How or after what maner we muſt doe it. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>,</hi> I haue vrged the duty it ſelfe by way of inſtruction &amp; reproofe. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>,</hi> Is ſet downe Arguments or Motiues therevnto. Many there are that haue briefly diſcourſed vpon this ſubiect, and I muſt needs confeſſe, my pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath constrained me to glean ſome bundles ofeares, which I haue found ſeattered here and there, in the fields of ſome of them. For which I hope no wiſe and indicious reader will thinke the worſe of my paines: for as the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders web is not to bee eſteemed the more becauſe it is wouen out of her owne bowels; ſo neither is the hony of the <hi>Bee</hi> the leſſe ſet by, becauſe it is ſuckt from divers flowers. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb facs="tcp:2806:8"/> it finde acceptance, I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to offer this poore mite of my penurie, amongſt the <hi>Talents,</hi> which others out of their plenty haue caſt into the offerings of God; yea whilſt many worthy and learned men lay vp their <hi>Talents</hi> in obſcuritie. I haue rather choſen to put my little to employment, for the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then in a ſullen diſdaine to hord vp much for myſelfe. I confeſſe my first studies vpon this point, and this impotent worke, like the Cripple at the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> had kept its owne couch till death, had not ſome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Angell</hi> troubled the water, and put it in, to make it goe abroad; and the rather, becauſe I knewe my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit &amp; vnworthy to handle this point being not ſo apt to giue, or receiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction as I ſhould. Take this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as a token of what I deſire, and ſhall ſtrine to he, not what I am: if thou canſt get any good by mee, bleſſe God, and I will follow thee ſo fast as I
<pb facs="tcp:2806:8"/> can. But leaſt I ſhould make my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting like the Citie of <hi>Mindus,</hi> with a faire and large gate, and the edifice but poore and little, I leaue both it and thee to the bleſsing of him, who alone giues increaſe of grace to all our good endeavours.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Richard Truman.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:2806:9"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN Memorandum.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Apostle</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them ſo to carry <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> themſelues, that they ſhould be <hi>blameleſſe and harmeleſse, the ſonnes of God, without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked and peruerſe nation, amongſt whom ſaith he, yee ſhine as lights in the world.</hi> Now as in that place the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would haue the <hi>Philippians</hi> imitate thoſe heauenly bodies in their light and influence, ſo hee ſtirres vp the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to imitate
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2806:10"/> their motion: and therefore as the <hi>Planets</hi> carried about by the ſway of the <hi>Heauens</hi> doe notwithſtanding keepe a proper courſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſo he admoniſheth all chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, that though in common and naturall courſes, they cannot but be carried by the ſway of the world; yet he vrgeth them to haue a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar and proper motion of grace and goodneſſe, contrary to the courſe of worldlings, and not to participate with the wicked in evill doing, but rather reproue their euill manners. <hi>Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 11,</note> 
                  <hi>workes of darkneſſe but reproue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">What it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to reproue.</note> 
                  <hi>them rather:</hi> Now from this place alſo we may briefly ſee the nature of <note place="margin">Dogeneres ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos times argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, Virg. Apparet virtus arguitur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> malis O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id. Ipſum peccan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> verbis, opera verà luce vitae arguimus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſe in loc.</note> reproofe, or what it is to reproue. The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which commonly is tranſlated by the word <hi>arguite,</hi> Reproue, ſignifieth properly to bring to light or make manifeſt, as <hi>Caluin</hi> &amp; other Expoſitors on that place obſerue. Now that is done
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2806:10"/> two waies, either by our words, or by our workes, by an holy contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in words, and by an heauenly contrariety of practiſe. So that to reproue, is nothing elſe but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and lay open to our brethren their faults, together with our owne diſlike of the ſame, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>How we muſt reproue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three things required in Reproofe</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THat this Chriſtian duty may <note place="margin">Three requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</note> be performed to the honour of God, and the good both of the reprouer and reproued, there are three things very requiſite and neceſſary, in all our reprehenſions. It is a common ſaying, euery good <hi>Phyſitian</hi> muſt haue three proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2806:11"/> An <hi>Eagles</hi> eye, a <hi>Ladies</hi> hand, and a <hi>Lyons</hi> heart. Now theſe three may ſerue as a fit <hi>Embleme,</hi> of three vertues, and ſiſter graces, herein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. <hi>Wiſdome, Gentleneſſe, and Courage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt requiſite is wiſdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt thing required in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, <note place="margin">Firſt requiſite wiſdome. In wiſdome a precedent and preſent diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> is <hi>wiſdome,</hi> &amp; that requires a double qualification one prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, before our reproofe, the other preſent in the action of our reproofe it ſelfe: the precedent condition ſtands likewiſe in two things, firſt in the knowledge of the fault. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in <hi>Authority</hi> to reproue, before we take it vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt precedent property of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we will reproue in wiſdome, <note place="margin">Firſt prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent property of wiſdome is knowledge of the fault.</note> then firſt we muſt be ſure, wee haue knowledge of the fault committed, and driue the nayle in a ſure place. It muſt bee made manifeſt by the light, and then we muſt reproue it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2806:11"/> the fault muſt not be controuerted, <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 13. <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur manifeſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> luce.</hi>
                  </note> or litigious, vpon ſuſpitious ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and flying reports of others, for ſo we may looſe our labour and friend at once, but if we doe mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fault vpon preſumptions and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities, from the reports of others then let our reproofe be Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, that if the offence reported of be not true, then they that told vs may beare our ſhame; but the ſafeſt courſe will be to ſtop our eares, and deny every odious report the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and of a certaintie to knowe before wee beleeue or reprehend. Thus the Lord himſelfe aduiſeth vs <hi>Thou ſhalt enquire and make ſearch, and aske diligently, and behold if it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>be truth and the thing certaine that ſuch abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is wrought amongſt you;</hi> and then according to equity we may proceed to correction and reproofe. Yea when God was to deale with as ſpurious a people, as the earth did beare, the ſonnes and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2806:12"/> daughters of whoredome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe it ſelfe, namely the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> the cry of whoſe ſinnes pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the heauens for vengeance, yet he would not deſtroy them vntill he came downe (as it were from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) and perceiued that the clamour <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 20. 21</note> of their ſinnes was iuſt againſt them. Almighty God that knoweth all <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omni potens Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, omnia ſcient, cur ante probationem quaſi dubitat, niſi vt gravita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis nobis exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum proponat, ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>la homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ante prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumamus quam propere. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>or. lib.</hi> 29 <hi>c.</hi> 23 <hi>Aequa iniquitas eſt &amp; punire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes &amp; non punire nocentes, Ber.</hi>
                  </note> things, ſeemeth to doubt of ſome thing before proofe bee made, for what cauſe? but to giue vs an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of grauitie, not to be light of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, or reproofe, in conceiuing evill of others, before we ſee things plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly proued: and indeed it is as great a ſinne, in this kind, to puniſh any man that is not guilty, as not to reproue when we behold a fault worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. But herein many men doe much miſchiefe to themſelues and others, who will take occaſion vpon any ſuſpitions and rumours, even from men of hoſtile and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous diſpoſitions to control<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2806:12"/> condemne others; or if they want an author for their aſpertion, then they broach adulterate and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gloſſes, hammered onely from the forge of their own falſhood, yea many will reproue and ſpeake ill of others hauing no more, in truth, to ſpeake againſt them, then the <hi>chiefe Priests</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> had to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> vnto <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>if he were not an evill doer, wee would not haue deliuered him vp vnto thee.</hi> Their bare acclamation &amp; clamour muſt be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d enough, even to the deſtruction and ruine of others, theſe are like vnto the <hi>Lion,</hi> that ſleepes with his eies open, they will ſeeme to the world, as if they knewe all things, whereas indeed they ſee nothing at all, and this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in many breeds nothing elſe, but diſſention and controuerſies, warres and rumours of warre, in good ſocieties, and a well gouerned Common-weale, yea amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2806:13"/> it breakes the very neck-bone of loue and amity, which can neuer be ſet againe. It is good therefore for vs not to let fly our bullet of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, in the face of any, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, which is perſpicuous &amp; evident; leaſt miſchiefe &amp; diſhonour cauſe that head-ſtrong and furious bullet, which wee ſhot into the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe campe, to retort to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our ſelues; yea it is farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to couer a fault when it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, then vpon vncertainties to reproue it, or to extend it when it is made knowne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second Antecedent required in wiſdome, is Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>wiſdome</hi> requires that <note place="margin">Second prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of wiſdome is to haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority. This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>poteſtas autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</hi>
                  </note> before we reproue, we ſhould haue authority therevnto, after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the fault. Now authoritie is either publike or priuate, publike authority is from the word, &amp; from the ſword, and belong either to the Miniſter or Magiſtrate, theſe as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2806:13"/> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth <hi>Titus,</hi> may <hi>ſpeake ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and rebuke with all authority.</hi> Yea as the Lord ſaith to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and <hi>Abſolon</hi> to his ſeruants, they muſt <note place="margin">Ioſh. 1. 9. 2. Sam. 13. 28.</note> be couragious and doe it becauſe God commandes them to ſtrike ſin. Priuate authority pertaineth to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">2 Priuate au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> chriſtian in his ſeuerall place to vſe this duty of loue, gouerning himſelfe with cautious, and due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: but here we muſt know, that every man is not bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, being but a priuate man, but when conueniencie doth offer it ſelfe; for wee are bound to reproue, as to giue almes, now wee are not bound in giuing almes, alwaies to ſeeke out perſons to whom we may giue, becauſe wee ſhall commonly finde enough obiects of pitty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeking for them, and then if we adminiſter comfort and helpe to thoſe wee meete, we haue done our duties: thus muſt wee doe in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, it is a publike debt wee owe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2806:14"/> to all men, and therefore if wee be but priuate men, it is not required of vs to enquire after, and ſearch out the faultes of others, to reprehend them, but if wee ſeaſonably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them as oft as we meet with them, wee haue performed as much as God requires at our handes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed euery man in his owne familie is a publike man, and may exerciſe his power, but a man hath no pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar charge ouer others, without he ſees a milde and friendly reproofe may take place: as for him that will take vpon him to reproue hee knowes not whom, in an abrupt and vnſeemely manner, performes hee knowes not what, and his action is ſtrained, as if a <hi>Iuſtice of peace</hi> ſhould looke for as much authority in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther country, as he can challenge at home. The beſt reproofe in this kinde, is our diſlike, and reſolution on the contrary, with <hi>Ioſhua, I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord;</hi> or with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2806:14"/> the <hi>Prophet Dauid, I will not ſit or</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>impii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debo.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>remaine with the wicked;</hi> that at leaſt, if we cannot better them, wee may keepe our ſelues from infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But here may be repoued many reprouets, and men of dogged na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yea not only ſo in themſelues, but ſuch as bring vp cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res to their owne handes, and ſend them fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about, to ſmell out the faults of others, that they themſelues may follow ſent the better. Fooliſh and diſtempered braines they are, taking vpon them, to reproue and correct their betters, hauing neither autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity nor calling to reproue, nor bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and benefit in concluſion, but rather diſaduantage and dammage themſelues, by their vnaduiſed car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. Theſe may rightly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>Pelican,</hi> that finding a fire neere her neſt, and fearing leaſt her young ones ſhould be burnt, ſhe ſtriues ſo much to blow it out, and to extinguiſh it with her winges,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2806:15"/> that at length ſhe burnes her ſelfe &amp; her young ones by her fooliſh pitty: thus many vnaduiſedly medling with the ſinnes of others proue ſo farre from helping them, that they rather fire their owne winges, then quench the flame and heat of ſinne in others. Therefore it is requiſite, that he that will reproue, haue a commiſſion and authority to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his action, for defect in this kinde, makes men contemned and reſiſted. The ſonnes of <hi>Sceua</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take vpon them a matter of great charity and conſequence, in caſting out diuells, in the name of Ieſus, but the diuells knowing they had no authority, <hi>for any ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reſiſted them, leapt vpon them</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 19. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>and preuailed againſt them, ſo that they fled away naked and wounded.</hi> Thus <hi>Vzza</hi> hauing no warrant for ſtaying the tottering <hi>Arke</hi> loſt his <note place="margin">1. Chr. 13. 9. 10</note> life for it. And thus men often times ſuffer as buſibodies in other mens <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 15.</note>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2806:15"/> matters. Better it is therefore to be ſilent till wee haue a calling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, &amp; to take S. <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell, <hi>To ſtudie to be quiet, and to meddle</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>with our owne buſineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſent qualification of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in reproofe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After wee haue ſearched into the <note place="margin">Preſent Qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of wiſdome wherein it conſiſts.</note> knowledge of the fault of another, and our owne authority to reproue him; which are the two maine pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, vpon whom the foundation ſtandeth, it is very neceſſary wee looke into the preſent qualification of wiſdome: and that conſiſts in conſideration of three circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 1. the <hi>Perſon</hi> whom wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. <note place="margin">in 3 thinges.</note> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> the <hi>Place</hi> where wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> when wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. In the <hi>Perſon</hi> we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, 1 his diſpoſition by nature. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Three things conſiderable in the perſon we reproue.</note> what his offences are, and thereafter temper our reproofes. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> wee muſt know, what he is in place, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward condition amongſt men.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2806:16"/>
               <p>Frſt wee muſt conſider of what <note place="margin">In the perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſider his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aturall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> temper and conſtitution hee is of, whom wee haue to deale with, and ſo demeane our ſelues in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe; for all men are not to bee handled alike, becauſe all are not qualified alike. Some are like <hi>Thornes</hi> (ſaith a moderne diuine) which being eaſily touched hurt not; but if hard and vnwarily, they fetch blood of the handes; others as <hi>Nettles,</hi> which if they bee nicely handled ſting and pricke, but if hardly and roughly they are pulled vp without harme, therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we take any man in hand, wee muſt know whether he be a <hi>Thorne</hi> or a <hi>Nettle,</hi> whether hee be of an harſh or mild diſpoſition, for many wee ſhall finde, that the more they are borne withall, the more outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they grow; which being ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, may bee reformed and reclaimed whereas all the faire meanes, and good wordes a man
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2806:16"/> can vſe will no whit better them; others there are of another minde, more ſtout hearted and manly, who in no hand will bee reclaimed by harſh courſes and ill languages, but are like the <hi>Indian Lama,</hi> a beaſt that will performe more for intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then a multitude of ſtripes, and a nod, or gentle admonition to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of <hi>a wiſe man) will doe more good, then an hundred ſtripes vpon the backe of a foole.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 17. 10.</note> With ſuch kinde of men wee muſt deale, as a skilfull <hi>Cooke,</hi> in roſting his meat, who that it may not burne, at firſt layes it a good way from the fite, for a little fire and a ſmall heat ſooner openeth the pores, &amp; heats to the bone, by reaſon of the little reſiſtance; then if it were at firſt put neere to the fire, which by reaſon of that oppoſition &amp; contrarietie of qualities, would ſhut the pores and ſo quickly burne the meat. Thus when wee are to reproue men of this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2806:17"/> quality, it's better to doe it by little and little, leaſt an ouer violent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe cauſes rather an oppoſition, then a capatious and pliable yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is not amiſſe to vſe both kindes, as wiſe ſouldiers ſtriuing to winne a <hi>Cittie,</hi> who ſome times goe forward with open and violent bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and ſome times by prudent policie; according as they ſee the condition of the ſtate they oppoſe. Yea let vs conſider with S. <hi>Paul</hi> and know whether wee ſhould <hi>come to them with a rod, or in loue, and in the ſpirit of meekeneſse,</hi> which muſt <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 21.</note> bee done vpon conſideration of the nature and quality of the reproued.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt conſider a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <note place="margin">2ly his courſe of life.</note> men that haue committed faults, worthy reproofe, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall courſe of their liues, whether they be leſſe or greater offenders, &amp; ſo temper our rebukes. Thus <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> giues vs an example, in reprou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of both conditions; when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2806:17"/> he ſaw <hi>the Hebrew and the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian fight, hee preſently drew his ſword and ſlew the Aegyptian;</hi> but when he <hi>ſaw the two Hebrewes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, hee ſaid to him that did the wrong, wherefore ſmiteſt thou thy fellow?</hi> Thus wee muſt giue euery <note place="margin">Exod 2. 12. 13.</note> man his proper portion, <hi>not caſting pearles to ſwine,</hi> nor yet giuing the <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 6.</note> true child a <hi>Serpent</hi> for a fiſh. Firſt <note place="margin">1 How to handle weake chriſtians. 1 Pet. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Cor. 3. 2.</note> ſome are new borne babes in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church, &amp; muſt be fed with milke; yea with the hony and the hony-combe of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of peace and mercy, leaſt they ſwallowing down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he great morſells of miſery from the <hi>Lambe</hi> of God, being not able to digeſt them, together with them they caſt vp their good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome nouriſhment; and here wee may quickly <hi>breake the bruiſed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 42 3.</note> 
                  <hi>reede, and quench the ſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing flaxe:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iude 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of theſe therefore we muſt <hi>haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. How to deale with men partly reclaimed.</note> 
                  <hi>making a difference.</hi> Others there are in the ſecond place, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2806:18"/> are in part reclaimed and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their fault, or there are in them manifeſt ſignes of ſpeedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, now here there is no place left for reproofe, but loue <hi>muſt couer a multitude of ſinnes:</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 8.</note> he that cannot wiſely accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to time and place digeſt and winke at ſmall faults, when there are true and ſtronge probabilities of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, <note place="margin">Qui neſtit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulare neſcit impera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et</note> from the party offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is vnfit to be a reprouer; ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent it is to ſuch men to haue borne the ſhame and correction of their former iniquities, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of the inceſtious perſon, whom hee would haue the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 7. <hi>Condonate illi &amp; conſolamini illum: id eſt, ita nunc eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te promp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ad ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcendu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; conſolandum ſicut tunc ſuiſtis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> obiurgan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Anſelm. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> no more for his ſinne, leaſt he ſhould be ſwallowed vp with over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much heauineſſe; but contrariwiſe he exhorts them to forgiue him and comfort him, and that with as much willingneſſe and freedome, as firſt they were forward to correct him and caſt him out of the Church for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2806:18"/> his offence. But herein many are exceedingly ouerſeene who though they perceiue ſome good alteration and change, in the life or manners of a friend or brother, yet they doe ſo ply him with continuall reprofes, that they rather hurt then helpe; &amp; through too much curioſity and ſtrictneſſe, ſpoyle where they might ſeaſonably better: theſe are like to <hi>Apelles Prentice,</hi> who coueting to mend the noſe marred the cheeke: or like the fooliſh <hi>Diar,</hi> who neuer <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Multi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ratrum peccata antiqua &amp; iam emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rigunt. Stella in Luc. cap.</hi> 17. v. 3. <hi>Nocentes punire ſupra meritum manifeſta ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas eſt, in quantum enim punitio excedit delictum, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tantum inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia punitur.</hi> 3ly How to reproue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter malefact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</note> thinkes his cloath blacke, till it bee burnt, yea ſometimes they rub vpon an old ſore, which hath beene hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led long agoe, and ſo moſt vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exceeding in puniſhment the nature of the offence, with much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice puniſh euen innocency it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and for want of iudgement in handling men of a good and tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature, they neuer leaue till they haue brought a good beginning to an euill end. Thirdly if they that ſin
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2806:19"/> be greater offenders, and ſuch as continue in ſinne daily and are more hardly reclaimed, then as S. <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth <hi>Timothie.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>rebuke;</hi> noting that if a bare reproofe will not ſerue, then we may deale more roughly with him: for good wordes and forbearance to ſuch is like a too haſtie ſalucing and skinning ouer a ſore, the feſter whereof breaketh out againe with more rage and danger: and as Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lightening doe more puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the aire, then the calmeſt Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, ſo the terrours of the law, and a ſharpe cenſure doe more better men of this condition, then milde &amp; pleaſant ſpeeches: here if wee deale with too much clemency, wee doe but only ſhake the ſheaues of ſinne, and lappe the branches of iniquity, and leaue the tree like that which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeakes of, with the ſtumpe <note place="margin">Daniel 4. 15.</note> and rootes in the ground, which in time will bring forth fruit againe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2806:19"/> it is better to lay the Axe to the root of the tree, &amp; to cut away all which God hath not planted, and if they will not be reclaimed by faire means <hi>to rebuke them ſharpely that they may be ſound in the faith,</hi> God hath <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 13.</note> made euery man in this kinde his brothers keeper, and a fiſher of men, therefore it behoues vs to doe like skilfull fiſhers, who fiſh not for all kinde of fiſh after one manner; when they angle they are priuate and ſtill, leaſt they fright away the fiſh: but when they ſet their nets to catch, then they plunge &amp; beat the riuers, and with a great clamour and noiſe they driue fiſh by force into their nets: ſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we come to catch ſome ſoules with the hooke of reproofe, we muſt fiſh priuately ſecretly and concealedly; alſo when wee fiſh to catch others wee muſt doe it <hi>magno ſtrepitu,</hi> with many great outcries and noiſes, that wee may <hi>compell</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 14 23.</note> 
                  <hi>them to come in,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> at one time
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2806:20"/> fiſhing droue three thouſand ſoules <note place="margin">Act. 2. 41.</note> into his net: otherwiſe the want of a little labour may daſh all our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hope and future ſucceſſe; they therefore, they that goe not through-ſtitch in their reproofes, &amp; handle not greater malefactors with greater ſeuerity, may doe them ſome good for the preſent, but not to the ſaueing of their ſoules: theſe deale like a faint hearted and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Phyſition, who by ſparing of an ounce or two of corrupt blood, which was better out then in, they leaue that behinde that taints &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the whole body againe: It is better therefore not to ſpare the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of a mans perſon, then to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſoule and body to bee deſtroied by ſinne, at the day of iudgement. Fourthly and laſtly, if wee ſee that <note place="margin">4ly What per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not to bee repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Prov. 17. 22.</note> thoſe wee reproue are vncorrigible, &amp; will not be bettered by reproofe, but harden their hearts againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: if they be the <hi>ſonnes of Ely,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 2. 12.</note>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2806:20"/> 
                  <hi>the ſonnes of Belial,</hi> paſt hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, if they be open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contemners of religion, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hating to be reproued, as ſome there be, whom a man can no ſooner reduce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin by reproofe, then they may take a <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in the maine Ocean with a net, then we may giue them ouer as <hi>Christ</hi> gaue ouer the <hi>Scribes, Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fulfill</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>the meaſure of their owne wretched</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 22. 11. <hi>Pereat, perdat, proſundat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>choice:</hi> and he that is vniuſt let him be vniuſt ſtill, and hee that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill: for to inſtruct and admoniſh this peruerſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, is but to <hi>caſt pearles</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>before ſwine, who will trample them vnder their feete, &amp; like doggs turne againe, and all to rent you,</hi> theſe men are like vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the milke of the <hi>Tygreſſe,</hi> the more ſalt is throwne into it, the freſher it is, ſuch whelpes are they of that monſter, that the more reproofe they haue to ſeaſon them, the freſher their ſinnes are in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2806:21"/> them: and wee ſhall euer finde that thoſe that are bent vpon villanie, with a full intent and reſolution, are made more violent by diſſuaſion; as a ſtrong ſtreame beeing reſiſted by floodgates, will ſwell ouer the banks &amp; as he that caſteth a ſtone againſt a marble pillar, doth not breake the marble, but in regard of the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cuſſion brings danger vpon himſelfe; thus he that reprou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an Adamantine and hardned heart ſhall for the ſeed that he hath ſowne of wholſome reproofe, in this vnprofitable and curſed ground, reape nothing for his paines, but the weedes and thornes of mockes and reproaches. For a <hi>ſcorner loueth not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>one that reproueth him.</hi> And hee that reproueth a ſcorner getteth <note place="margin">Prov. 9. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe ſhame, and he that rebuketh a wicked man getteth himſelf a blot:</hi> better therefore is it to be ſilent, then to ſtirre vp <hi>Hornets</hi> about our eares, and to thruſt our handes into a waſpes neſt.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2806:21"/>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, wiſdome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <note place="margin">3. Wiſdome is to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſider the outward quality of him we reproue. 1. How to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</note> that our reproofe be ordered with an aduiſed conſideration of the outward quality and condition of them we reproue, with a reſpect to their place and age, as if they be our inferiours, eſpecially ſuch as any way haue relation to vs, or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency vpon vs, then wee may doe it with more freedome and authority. If they be our equalls, then not by <note place="margin">2. Equals. <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rem non habet impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. Vt amica com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monefactione facilius illi in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducantur. Calv. in</hi> 1. <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 5. 3. Superiours.</note> an imperious command but by a louing and friendly commonition, and aduertiſement, that wee may bring them into the right way. But if they be our ſuperiours in place &amp; age, or either waies, then wee muſt carry our ſelues with reuerent and ſubmiſſe exhortations, according to that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie, Rebuke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>not an elder, but entreat him as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> eſpecially if he bee a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall <hi>Elder</hi> and a Father in Gods Church, that revealeth the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God to his people, here muſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2806:22"/> a ſingular care bee taken in gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our tongues in reproofe and reprehenſion. But as it was the ſinne of Iſrael, ſo is it of our times. This people are as they that rebuke the Prieſt: yea wee ſhall finde <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4 4.</note> and <hi>Rurall Swine,</hi> that will make no more to reproue the life &amp; doctrine of the miniſtry, then they will doe to correct a miſhapen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, or to giue their horſe the laſh, when they are offended with him. But let them knowe that if <hi>Cham</hi> was curſed for ſporting at <hi>Noahs</hi> nakedneſſe, and yet ſpake the truth; thrice curſed ſhall they bee, that <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 22.</note> without a cauſe, make aſhamed their ſpirituall Fathers in the Lord. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we deſire to doe good in this louely office of reproofe, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the perſon whom we reproue, and therein his naturall temperature his courſe of life, the quality of his offence, as alſo his outward conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and accordingly let vs doe as an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2806:22"/> expert Muſitian, who in ſetting an inſtrument in tune, doth ſometimes winde vp his ſtrings, &amp; ſometimes let them downe againe: ſo, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſerues, let vs learne to be earneſt and gentle in our reproofes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of wiſdome, &amp; then may we expect a good ſucceſſe to attend our endeauours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in wiſe reproofe is the Place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <note place="margin">2 Place where we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. Private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe for a private offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> to bee conſidered in wiſe and diſcreet reproofe, is the <hi>Place</hi> where we muſt reproue. Now if it be a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate offence, it muſt bee priuately handled, according to our <hi>Sauiours</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 15. 16 &amp;c.</note> direction. <hi>If thy brother ſhall treſpaſse against thee, goe &amp; tell him his fault betweene thee and him alone:</hi> but if ſecret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>duertiſements will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, then we may goe to him more openly. But if he will not heare thee, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take with thee one or two more,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2806:23"/> that in the mouth of one or two wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes euery word may bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and if hee ſhall neglect to heare them, then wee may relate it more publikely, and tell it to the Church. For as the <hi>Damſell was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5 41. Luk 7. 14. Ioh. 11. 43.</note> 
                  <hi>vp within the dores: the widowes ſonne without the gates: and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus before a great multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> ſo we muſt handle ſome priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in ſecret, others more open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the third kinde in publike, as the inceſtuous perſon was vſed. If we can doe good with them by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2. 6.</note> inſtructions and corrections, then we need goe no farther: if that will not ſerue, wee may<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> relate the matter before ſome others; if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe will worke with the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient we haue in hand, then we may tell it to the Church, that if the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders will not be amended yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <note place="margin">Publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe for pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like offenders</note> may be preſerued from conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: This made S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> name <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the <hi>Copper-ſmith</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2806:23"/> to the intent he might beware <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 15.</note> of him. <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo nominateth <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes</hi> for Chriſtians to take heed <note place="margin">3. Ioh 9.</note> of him; but this was in a waightie and publike matter, euen for the <note place="margin">Qualification for a publique reproofe. Gen. 2. 23. <hi>Quia proximus duo bona habes, famam ſciticet &amp; conſcientiam quae duo ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſunt in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſieri poteſt. Sed ſi po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſeruan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam teneris fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. Ideo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culte corripien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt. Sed ſi occulte monitus noluerit emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dari, tunc quiae conſcientia eſt maius bonum quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ama, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt, fama periclitetur, vt conſcientia non pereas. Stella in Luc. cap. v.</hi> 3.</note> good of the whole Church, &amp; this kinde of reproofe muſt not be vſed, but in like caſes; as for ſmall &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate offences, or for men which fall of infirmity, they muſt be vſed with all honeſt priuacie that may be: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauing our ſelues like <hi>Noahs</hi> good ſoones, who when their Father had diſcouered his ſecrets in time of his drunkenneſſe, they turned their backes vpon his ſhame, and vttered not a word; which giues vs to note, that the ſinnes of other men wee muſt modeſtly hide, &amp; ſilently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, with the beſt preſeruation we can of the credit of the delinquent. But if we cannot preſerue the ſoule and conſcience of a man without blemiſhing his credit, it is better to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndanger the one, then that we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2806:24"/> the other to periſh; as one large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſeth that caution. But in this caſe many are to be taxed of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, who deale with their brethren as the <hi>Iews</hi> did with <hi>Chriſt</hi> who when they came to ſpeake of his miracles and great workes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed his name, <hi>Hic homo, this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low doth many miracles,</hi> but when <note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 47.</note> they wrote the title of his fained crime on the tree, then they maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly publiſhed his name, not with <hi>hic homo,</hi> but <hi>Ieſus of Nazaret King</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 19. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Iewes, and in three famous tongues, Hebrew, Greeke, &amp; Latine,</hi> written in capitall letters that all men might runne &amp; reade it. There is a generation of men who in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the virtues of others are very ſparing and remiſſe, but in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a vice (though but ſuppoſed) they write infamie vpon their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, with the pen of a <hi>Diamond,</hi> which cannot be blotted out. Thus they cruelly rend the good name of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2806:24"/> their neighbours, and that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in any place or company, and oftentimes it falleth out, that in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of mirth and feaſting, their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt muſicke is, to talke of the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and infirmities of others, yea ſometimes malitiouſly, before the company of ſuch as with whom the party offending deſires to retaine loue and a good opinion; and this is a moſt cruell and wicked hoſtility, for nature and grace doe teach vs, to maintaine the good names of one another, and though we ſhould publikely condemne a diſorder, yet to ſpare the priuate perſon of any <note place="margin">Parcere perſon is dicere de vitiis. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, bellum cum vitiis, Aug.</note> man. Which rule if wee rightly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, we may confidently truſt, that as our paſſage in reprouing is good and honeſt, ſo our end will proue ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall &amp; proſperous, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and reformation of him we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third generall circumstance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe reproofe is the Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2806:25"/>
               <p>The third generall circumſtance <note place="margin">3. The Time when we muſt reproue, and that threefold 1. Timely. <hi>Nullum medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, niſi qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d opportune a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</hi>
                  </note> in wiſe reprouing is to take a due, and fit proportion of <hi>Time.</hi> As firſt, that we reproue betimes. 2 That our reproofe be ſeaſonable. 3 That wee continue in reprouing. Firſt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe muſt bee <hi>Timely,</hi> before the patient be paſt cure, for no ſalue is ſauing being adminiſtred after a fit time, and as if there be a fraction or diſlocation in our bones or ioints, the ſooner the <hi>Chirurgian</hi> takes it in hand, the eaſier it is to bee reſtored, ſo ſinne, which is the diſtortion of the ſoule, the ſooner it is reproued, the more eaſily it is amended; Saint <hi>Iude</hi> compares ſinne to a fire, and <note place="margin">Iude. 23.</note> therefore hee would haue ſinners pulled out of the fire, or ſnatched out with all haſt, before they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; which muſt bee done by a ſeaſonable and timely rebuke. But herein many fayle, who neuer admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter phyſicke till the patient bee paſt cures nor caſt on water till the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2806:25"/> houſe be burnt to the ground, they ſuffer their friend or brother to liue ſo long in ſinne, till he bee <hi>hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 13.</note> and herein many parents with <hi>Eli,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 29.</note> put off reproofe ſo long, that their children grow impudent in ſin, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, paſt amendment. This kinde of reproofe is like the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which the <hi>Porter</hi> gaue to <hi>Cato</hi> who after hee had ſtricken him on the eare wiſht him to beware. Better is the timely ſtroake of reproofe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinne, then that ſinne ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably ſtrike the ſoule to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly the time muſt be ſeaſonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our Time muſt be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, <note place="margin">2. Our time muſt be ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</note> when the delinquent is moſt capable of reproofe. Firſt, not when a man is in diſtreſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, <note place="margin">1. Not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</note> a troubled ſpirit is vnwilling to heare rebuke, and we ſhall finde reproofe like <hi>Hony,</hi> which though it be ſweet and pleaſant, yet if it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2806:26"/> to <hi>Vicers</hi> and ill affected me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, it is very painefull and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Secondly, wee muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue in time of exceſſe and riot; &amp; <note place="margin">Not in time of exceſſe. <hi>Non cum mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus exceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> eſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> cum ſe re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tit. Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 3. <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Phyſitians</hi> forbid to apply medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines when the hot fit &amp; paroxiſme rageth, and to giue it when the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity ſlacketh; ſo muſt this phiſick of the ſoule be applied at ſuch times as the patient is apteſt to receiue it, &amp; not in a burning diſtemper. Here we muſt <hi>giue place to wrath.</hi> Sinne <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 19. <hi>Dam furor in curſu eſt cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ti caede furori. Ov.</hi> ludg. 8. 5.</note> in theſe men muſt be ouercome like the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Ai</hi> by retiring from it for a ſeaſon, and not by too furious an on-ſet. This courſe tooke wiſe and virtuous <hi>Abigail,</hi> ſhe would not tell <hi>Nabal of his drunkenneſſe till he</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>was awake from this wine,</hi> ſhe knewe that a diſtemper was no ſeaſon for a man to be bettered by reproofe: ſhe dealt with her husband, as one that hath the ouerſight of <hi>Bees,</hi> who dares not at all times touch his own <hi>Hiues,</hi> if the <hi>Bees</hi> be angry and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2806:26"/> She ſaw how far he was wide of reaſon, and how ſhe might incur danger herſelfe, therefore for that time ſhe leaues him: leaſt he ſhould like a mad man not onely haue reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her Phyſicke, but alſo ſtroue to <note place="margin">More Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci non ſolum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellat, ſed &amp; mordere te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> medici manum. Ber.</note> bite the hand of the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> as a <hi>Father</hi> in another caſe much like this, ſpeakes. And therefore wee read that <hi>Alexander</hi> killed <hi>Clitus</hi> his intimate and familiar, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued him of drunkenneſſe, in the midſt of his cups. Hee that in theſe caſes will follow truth too neere the heeles, it may happily ſtrike out his <note place="margin">Ad penetendum properat, cito qui iudicat.</note> teeth. He that throwes a ſtone thus raſhly and vnaduiſedly into the aire it may fall downe vpon his owne head. A man that will reproue men in ſuch heats and furies, is like vnto a fooliſh <hi>ſhepheard,</hi> who ſeeing two furious <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> runne together in full ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, thruſts himſelfe between them, and ſo abides the ſtroake of both. Or like vnto the <hi>Bee</hi> which in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2806:27"/> a teſtie peeuiſhneſſe, ſtings another <note place="margin">Plin. hiſt. nat.</note> &amp; looſeth at once her own ſtrength and life. Thus hee that in this caſe will take vpon him to reproue and correct the faults of others, had need take heed, that he runne not vpon his owne miſchiefe and ruine; &amp; whilſt <hi>he thus bites and devoures another,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>he be conſumed of another himſelfe.</hi> Therefore for our owne ſafety, and for the benefit of the reproued, let vs be carefull to make choice of ſuch a time, when his heart is moſt plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to correction and diſcipline, and this will adde grace and comelineſſe to our reproofe; <hi>For a word fitly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is like apples of gold in pictures</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 11. 12</note> 
                  <hi>of ſiluer, as an earing of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, ſo is a wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouer to an obedient eare.</hi> And what can commend a man, or make him ſhine ſo bright, as that which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>M Cleaver</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place.</note> helpeth to remoue away the ragges of his corruption, and further him to repentance that he <hi>may be cladde</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2806:27"/> 
                  <hi>with righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, Reproofe muſt be continued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the laſt circumſtance of <note place="margin">3. Reproofe muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued. Gal. 6. 9.</note> time is, that our reproofe bee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: In this caſe wee muſt <hi>not bee weary of well doing.</hi> But as S. <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth vs, we muſt <hi>reproue, rebuke,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>exhort with all long ſuffering.</hi> But herein is to be admired the ſtrange carriage and impatience of many, who hauing told men of their faults and often reproued them for the ſame, they quickly grow weary of this Chriſtian duty, and in ſpleene &amp; choller forſake thoſe which God hath not forſaken: whereas euery man ſhould be grauid and in child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, for the new-birth of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and herein a man muſt imitate a woman with child, whoſe time is at hand; and then is poſſeſſed with feare and hope, and theſe two ſtriue as the two twins in <hi>Rebecca's</hi> womb her ſorrow makes her carefull, how <note place="margin">Gen. 25. 22. 23</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2806:28"/> ſhe ſhould bee deliuered, but her hope ſtayes her heart, firſt knowing that her miſery is common and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to all women in her caſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that ſhee is not likely to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her miſery long. Thirdly becauſe ſhe hopes the end of her paine will be the beginning of her ioy. Thus muſt wee bee affected for the new birth of our brethren, wee muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in ſorrow, and (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>My little children of whom I tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>in child birth:</hi> our patience muſt be much for thoſe that are yet without, and withall our ſorrow muſt bee mixed with hope, that though the new birth of grace in our brethren, be like that of nature, <hi>lachrinioſa,</hi> painefull, yet let vs with patience expect their amendment, hoping that the concluſion may ſweeten all, and that the ende of our eare may bee the beginning of their cure. But if any ſhall obiect and ſay, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> I haue ſo often reproued ſuch a man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2806:28"/> and yet perceiue no alteration and change, which makes me ſo weary, I can hold out no longer. I anſwere, take theſe motiues, to make thee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> in this friendly office: Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider <note place="margin">Motiues to make vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Motiue.</note> that it is not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enting the eares of any man, with ſharpe and bitter words, that will doe much good, but it is the continuance of wiſe reprehenſion that gets the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: reproofes are like the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <note place="margin">Gutta ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idem non v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſed ſape ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. Sic homo ſit iuſtus, non v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſed ſape mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</note> of water vpon a ſtone, which makes not impreſſion by force and violence, but by continuall drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. A man commonly is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwaighed with words of pounds and Talents, mighty and dreadfull ſpeeches, theſe ſeildome make any penetration in the heart of a ſinner: but when in a milde and ſoftly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, we continue in our reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; when our words ſhall drop as raine, and our ſpeeches diſtill ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as dew, we ſhall make a hard and ſtonie heart euen to bend, breake &amp;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2806:29"/> yeeld, and then <hi>a broken heart the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 17. a Motiue.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord will not deſpiſe.</hi> Secondly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how hard a thing it is for a man to be reclaimed from his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall corruptions; and that is intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the two words which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tongue giues for man. The firſt ſhewes his weakneſſe by creation, as <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> made of the earth, the weakeſt and baſeſt of the <hi>Elements:</hi> the ſecond expreſſeth his weakneſſe by the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> mortiferous and deadly ſickneſſe, his prevarication, and firſt fall brought him vnto. So that if wee rightly conſider it, wee haue more reaſon to wonder at the infinite pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience <note place="margin">Qui miſeram inſtabilem fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilem ac depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatam bominis naturam conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derant, illis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis mirum eſt, quod memor il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius eſt Deus, quam quod ille ſubinde peccat. Muſc. in Gal.</note> of God, in ſuffering the ſins of man: then to admire at his often tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſing the law of god. Every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the time of his effectuall calling is like vnto a chained priſoner, who is not able to goe whether hee would, or to performe what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; yea, when the chaines are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from off his legges, hee will halt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2806:29"/> and complaine a long time after, of his want of agilitie and nimbleneſſe, to vſe his ioints. Thus, before our calling is it with euery man, no man can moue hand or foot to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of any good action: and when a man hath ſhaken off the irons of ſinne, wherewith hee was holden and reſtrained, yet a long time after hee will feele, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of much want of ſtrength, &amp; be ſenſible of a great meaſure of lameneſſe, &amp; ſtiffeneſſe in the ioints of his ſoule, occaſioned by the bonds and chaines of ſinne. It is <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 15. 18. 24. 25.</note> ſtoried of one of our owne countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De Anſelmo in vita eius.</note> that being in his Peripateticall and walking ſtudies in the fields, vpon a certaine time caſt his eye vpon a ſhepheards boy, who hauing caught a bird, tied a ſtone to the leg thereof, by which meanes the bird could no ſooner mount and ſoare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, but the ſtone drew her downe againe: whereupon the reuerent &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2806:30"/> learned man fell a weeping, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doled the miſerable eſtate of man by nature; who could no ſooner by Godly thoughts &amp; contemplations endeauour to aſſcend vp into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but his corruptions and concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences forthwith enforced him to the earth againe, the due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which ſhould moue vs to patience and continuance in this duty, and withall know and reſolue, that if at length, by our wiſe and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable rebukes, wee can winne a ſoule to God, that then our labour is well beſtowed. Therefore in the third place, to continue our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, <note place="margin">3. motiue.</note> let vs conſider that man by nature is wonderfull forgetfull of good inſtruction &amp; reproofe: now, wee can neuer teach that thing too <note place="margin">Nunquam nimis dicitur, quod nunquam ſatis diſcitur. Sen.</note> much, which a man can neuer ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently learne; no man can liue ſo ſtrictly but he hath continuall need to be put in minde of his ill courſes, for a mans memory with <hi>Pharoas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 40. 23.</note>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2806:30"/> 
                  <hi>Butler,</hi> will ſoone be turned into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe; eſpecially in good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for therein it is like a <hi>ſieue,</hi> which holdes faſt the courſe brans, but lets the fine flower fall away. Therefore S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Take heede vnto thy doctrine, and continue in it, for in ſo doing thou ſhalt ſaue thy ſelfe, and them that heare thee,</hi> and thus may I ſay to euery reprouer, take heed vnto thy reproofe, and continue in it; for in ſo doing, thou ſhalt get a good reward to thy ſoule, and ſaue the ſoule of him thou reproueſt. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">4 motiue.</note> and laſtly, let ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> apprehenſion be continued, becauſe it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God that ſo we ſhould doe, &amp; therefore when S. <hi>Peter</hi> asked our <hi>Sauiour, How often ſhall my brother</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 21. 22 Luk. 17. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinne againſt me and I forgiue him? till ſeuen times? Ieſus faith vnto him, I ſay not vnto thee vntill ſeuen times, but vntill ſeuenty ſeuen times,</hi> whereby wee are taught that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2806:31"/> if wee cannot reforme ſinners, ſo ſoone as we would, yet we muſt not giue them ouer, but reproue <hi>quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es toties,</hi> as often as they ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; and thus wee ought to beare one anothers burthen, that if it bee poſſible we may conuert the ſinners <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 2.</note> to God: and euery man that will wiſely reproue muſt in concluſion <hi>open his mouth with wiſdome as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31. 26. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in ſapientia vel ſapienter.</hi> Eſa. 50. 4.</note> ſpeakes of a good huſwife, &amp; ſpeake a word in ſeaſon, to him that is weary and that word of reproofe muſt needs bee alwaies ſeasonable, which with wiſdome is directed to the offender, ſo often as hee doth tranſgreſſe, and therefore as needfull it is to continue (yea and farre more neceſſary) then to begin a reproofe at firſt, ſeeing the concluſion of <note place="margin">Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>trantia virtutum ſola cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atur.</note> every good act is that which crownes it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2806:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>The Second property of our reproofe, is Gentleneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſecond property where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with euery reproofe muſt <note place="margin">2 Property in a reprouer.</note> be adorned is <hi>Gentleneſſe and clemency,</hi> a ſober, mild, louing and curteous carriage. Wee muſt deale with malefactors as <hi>Lot</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued himſelfe towards the wicked <hi>Sodomites,</hi> who when they would haue pulled downe his houſe vpon his head, hee reproued them with meekeneſſe, and by way of petition, <hi>I pray you brethren doe not ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly.</hi> Thus <hi>Ioſhua</hi> behaued himſelfe <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 7.</note> towards <hi>Achan, My ſonne giue I pray thee, glory to the Lord God of Iſrael, &amp; make confeſsion vnto him,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh. 7. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and tell me now what thou haſt done,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2806:32"/> 
                  <hi>hide it not from me.</hi> Where wee ſee his ſpeech was neither filled with te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Battologies,</hi> nor with inuectiue bitterneſſe, but hee reproued him <note place="margin">Auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. open tune, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</note> with as few and friendly words as clemency could inuent, with a ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and friendly increpation, and yet his reprehenſion was fitly and powerfully ſpoken, a pregnant and imitable example of a good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature wee haue in <hi>Nathan</hi> with his dealling with <hi>Dauid,</hi> one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet with another, hee comes not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hem adulter, homicida, latro, Aug. in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar. in</hi> Pſal. 51. 2 Sam. 16. 13. Pſal. 141 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Perc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> me influs miſericor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dia.</hi>
                  </note> with railings and reuilings, out vpon thee thou adulterer, thou murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, thou theefe: not like a curſed and railing <hi>Shemei,</hi> but in a coole and gentle temper hee ſtrucke at his impoſtume, and let out the corrupt bloud. And therefore the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth vnto the <hi>Lord, Let the righteous ſmite me with leniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nomen</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>commode reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui poteſt in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbium cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Calvin. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and gentleneſse, as the Hebrew</hi> text plainely declareth, or gently and modeſtly, as one obſerueth vpon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2806:32"/> that place. Now if <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, a man according to Gods owne heart, doth thus deſire to bee dealt withall, then ſurely it is fit we ſhould deale no worſe one with another, for the better perſwaſion to this kinde of dealing, (let the malefactor be what hee will,) wee muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue him with gall &amp; bitterneſſe, for <hi>Michaell the Archangell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iude. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>with the diuell himſelfe, durſt not bring againſt him a railing accuſation, but ſaid, The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thee,</hi> yea ſo farre ſhould wee be from the intemperature of a curſt and bitter reprehenſion, that wee ſhould turne our cholor into a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and chriſtian compaſſion when we reproue a fault, and as a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> being to cutte his only ſonne, handleth him tenderly and ſoftly, and cutteth and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and weepeth and cutteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; ſo our bowels ſhould be filled with compaſſion, at the correction
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2806:33"/> and bettering of a diſtempered ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In gentleneſse two requiſites</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in a beneuolous and curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">In gentle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe two things tequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite.</note> reprehenſion two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite. Firſt a gentle inſtruction or admonition to make way for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, <note place="margin">1 A milde admonition.</note> according to that of <hi>S. Paul.</hi> In meekenſſe inſtruct them that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and therefore hee exhorteth-Timothie to conioyne <hi>reproofe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and exhortation,</hi> and indeed if theſe be ſeparated, wee cannot haue ſuch proſperous ſucceſſe as wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; becauſe inſtruction ſerues to encourage in goodneſſe, &amp; reproofe to reſtraine from ſinne, and thoſe that reproue and correct, and doe it not with admonitions and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are like to thoſe that are often ſnuffing the light, but forget to put oyle into the <hi>Lampe,</hi> for want of which it quickly goes out of it ſelfe. Therefore wee muſt be profitable (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Scripture) to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tim. 3. 16.</note>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2806:33"/> 
                  <hi>teach, to improue, to correct and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſse,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly wee ſhall finde inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on make way for reproofe, and win that audience which an vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and prepoſterous anger cannot attaine. They that reproue with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, are like to fooliſh Threſhers, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euer tappe the corne in the ſheafe gently, but laying on with mighty and powerfull ſtroakes, they make the good graine fly into euery cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſcatter that abroad which gentle and leaſurely labour might haue preſerued. Therefore let vs begin gently with friendly inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and when a man will endure this tapping, then ſtrike harder, or elſe wee ſhall but looſe our labour, for neceſſary is it that euery repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue the <hi>reproofes of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 6. 23. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>increpationes eruditionis.</hi>
                  </note> which being poſſeſſed with an attractiue vertue, cannot but winne audience and reſpect, that correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or reproue may haue the ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2806:34"/> working.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second requiſite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly it is very neceſſary that in our reproofes wee mingle ſome <note place="margin">2 A wiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of any good partes.</note> kind commendations of thoſe good partes and vertues wee ſee in the partie offending. Thus it is in the <hi>Poet, O Achilles, &amp;c.</hi> As much as if he ſhould haue ſaid, what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come now of thy courage and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which filled the whole world with thy honour &amp; renowne? How cometh it to paſſe that thou art thus retired, and haſt ſhamefully brought to infamie all thoſe excellent parts and valiant acts by thee peformed? Thus hauing awaked him out of his idleneſſe and ſecuritie, he ſtirres him vp to farther imployment, and ſo <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a.</note> informes him how hee may recouer and get againe his former honor, &amp; thus muſt wee deale with men of worthie and noble partes, putting them in minde of ſuch vertues and graces they poſſeſſe, and this will
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2806:34"/> Vſher reproofe to come before the face of the party offending; for man naturally is like vnto waxe, which being cold is ſo hard; that it admits of no impreſſion: but being once hot, it becomes ſoft, and plyable to any impreſſion at all. The minde of man though it be naturally hard &amp; vntractible, yet being made hot by curteous and wiſe approbations, it becomes fit to receiue the engraue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of correction and reproofe, &amp; as when a ſhower hath moiſtened the earth, then it is fitteſt to pluck vp weedes, and caſt in good graine. So when louing and kinde ſpeeches haue mollified a mans heart, then he is fitteſt to haue ſinne pulled out of his ſoule, and to receiue the good ſeede of wholſome reproofe; for the memory of former vertues cannot but touch the minde with a noble &amp; feeling ſhame of preſent faults. Therefore as thoſe that giue worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede for the wormes, to children,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2806:35"/> doe ſweeten it with ſomewhat that they may take the medicine more willingly, or as thoſe that giue bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pills to queaſie ſtomacked pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, doe wrappe them vp in ſome conſerue to the intent they may take them without offence. Thus let vs make a prepatatiue to reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, with ſome louing preamble of their deſerued commendations which may make way for their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall purgation; and be (as it were a bait) to hide the hooke of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, to catch the ſoules of them we fiſh for. But alaſſe too too many there are, who deale harſhly and barbarouſly in their carriages, and rather hurte then doe good to the reprouer, and all becauſe the ſalue proues worſe then the fore. Theſe kinde of people are like vnto thoſe mentioned in the old law, who ſtriking with the axe to cut downe the tree, <hi>the head ſlips from the helue, and hits his neighbour &amp; kils</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 19. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2806:35"/> 
                  <hi>him.</hi> Thus ſuch as reprehend others too curſtly, doe make the head of the Axe fly from the helue, and kill their brethren vnaduiſedly, and whereas with the good husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man they ſhould but lappe with the pruining knife, they hew downe <note place="margin">Ioh. 15. 2.</note> with the axe of iudgement, and ſuch as theſe goe about to amend the faults of others (according to the old prouerbe) as the <hi>Diuell</hi> did to ſet his dames legge, for whereas hee ſhould haue ſet it aright, he burſt it quite aſunder. But may not a man <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> vſe what freedome hee ſeemes meet ouer ſuch he hath in authority, as if my child, my ſeruant, or any that is in ſubiection to me offend, may I not then reproue them, as I pleaſe. I anſwere, the more authority thou <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> haſt, thou haſt the more freedome: yet take heede thou doſt not abuſe thy liberty, there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſupremacy and tyrannic, thou art a <hi>King</hi> in thy owne houſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2806:36"/> and teritories, but take heede thou proue not a Tyrant: leaſt thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thoſe that are in ſubiection vnto thee; the bitterneſſe of an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſticketh cloſe to any man; but the fury of him to whom wee haue relation, wounds a good nature moſt of all: as when <hi>Caſar</hi> ſaw the hand of his ſonne <hi>Brutus</hi> againſt him, then his heart was done, and crye: out <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, what thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my ſonne <hi>Brutus?</hi> Thus the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious cruelty of a friend, in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reproofes, ſtrikes with as ſtrang a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement the heart of him that is reproued. O but the faults of ſuch a <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>
                  </label> one who is vnder my charge are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, and therefore I will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer him nor ſuccor him. I anſwere, take heede thou ſuffer not <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> the ſame ſinnes in thy ſelfe: at the leaſt that thou beare not the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of a ſinfull reproofe in thy ſelfe, by exonerating another of his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, againe thou canſt finde in thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2806:36"/> heart to feede a curſt <hi>curre</hi> a ſpotted <hi>Beaſt,</hi> a wanton <hi>Ape,</hi> and a cruel <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but the ſimplicity, blemiſhes and ſinnes of thy dependents thou canſt not endure, nor them for their ſinnes ſake. Be as wiſe as thou canſt to beat downe ſinne, but take heede thou proneſt not vnnaturall. Be not thou like a <hi>Dragon</hi> in the Wilderneſſe cruell to her young; nor like the <hi>Oſtrich,</hi> which forbearing ſuſtenance <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am 43.</note> expoſeth her young ones to the wide world, as <hi>Moſes</hi> Parents their <note place="margin">Exod. 2. 3.</note> ſonne to the waues of the riuer. Let not parents proue without naturall <note place="margin">2 Tim 3. 3. Gen. 49. 5.</note> affection, neither <hi>Let instruments of cruelty be in their habitation,</hi> as it is ſaid of <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eon and Leui,</hi> and as they <note place="margin">Sce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt. Iaſon &amp; magis Scelus Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ought not to be extreame to marke what is done amiſſe, ſo neither to reproue what is amiſſe: but with all gentleneſſe and compaſſion reproue ſuch ſinnes in their children, as they haue deriued to them from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2806:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three cauſes of bitter reproofe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Three cauſes of hit ter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now if any man ſhall demand a reaſon of mee why many men deale thus curſtly with ſuch as offend: I will giue him three maine cauſes of ſuch inhumanitie, the firſt is <hi>vaine glory,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Loquacitie,</hi> &amp; the third <hi>Enuy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place wee ſhall finde <note place="margin">1 Cauſe vaine glory.</note> that <hi>vaine glory</hi> is a great cauſe of this vnkinde dealing, and ſtirreth vp men to controll the faults of others, out of a ſecret ſelfeloue to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. The <hi>Phariſee</hi> lookes vpon the publique faults of others, and with an indigne condemning and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing of others, ſtriues for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe to his owne perſon. <hi>I am not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 11. 12. <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſum ſicut cateri, non ſicut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>as other men are, &amp;c. nor even as this Publican.</hi> Thus there are many men, who from a triumphing and imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inſultation ouer the falls of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea from peremptorie and malignant forgeries and fancies of their owne, proclaime the faults of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2806:37"/> other men, who are ſeauen times more iuſt then themſelues, thinking that by the eclypſing the light of others, they ſhall make themſelues ſhine more bright in the eyes of the world. This is as if the <hi>Moone</hi> ſhould reioyce at the night and abſence of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and thereby goe about to make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that all light &amp; influence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from her ſelfe. But let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe that they that ſtriue to build ſuch a <hi>Babel</hi> of pride and vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vpon the ruines of other mens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, ſhall ſoone be brought to confuſion for their paines. And like <hi>Flies,</hi> whilſt they ſtriue to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh &amp; put out the light of others they ſhall torment and burne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the flame. I could wiſh this fault were not too common even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſonnes of <hi>Levi</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, who ſtriue like <hi>Abſolon</hi> to <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>steale away the hearts of the people,</hi> and that by diſcouering and aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2806:38"/> the faults of their fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, whereby they may winne more renowne to themſelues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common &amp; vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and as the <hi>Apostle S. Paul</hi> ſpeaks <hi>They are puffed vp rather then</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>mourne for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem that haue done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> And as a <hi>Cypher</hi> ſet after a <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> makes it of more account and valuation, then if it ſtood by it ſelfe. So they thinke they ſhall neuer bee raiſed to the height of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mindes, but by the weakneſſe of the like compariſons: thus the ſilly <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Farn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>by in Ep. ante Trag. Sen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Graſſe-hopper</hi> and the <hi>Piſmire</hi> in their generations proue moſt dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate in their owne kindes. And they that are moſt vnable of all to reſiſt, become moſt cruell enimies one to another, Diſcouering a great meaſure of hypocriſie to the world and to God. <hi>For how can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 5. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>when they ſeeke glory one from another?</hi> And this is the firſt reaſon or cauſe, why many men reproue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2806:38"/> with ſuch ſtrictneſſe and auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, becauſe by the looking into their blemiſhes, and imperfections, they think more cleerly to ſet forth their owne beauty and comelineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſe the ſecond.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond cauſe is loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe proceeds from <hi>Loquacity</hi> &amp; a looſeneſſe of ſpeech, as when men haue ſmall or no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, they fall into diſcourſe of the liues &amp; manners of others: theſe are like vnto S. <hi>Pauls widowes, they learne to be idle, wandering about</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Non ſolum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſae, ſed &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſae, id eſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum facta &amp; negligentes ſua, &amp; ſtudentes ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſemper au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. Anſelm. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>from houſe to houſe; and not only idle but tatlers alſo, and buſie-bodies, ſpeaking things which they ought not.</hi> They are ſuch as caſt not an eie vpon their owne faults, but are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies diſcouering the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with itching &amp; Athenian eares. I may rightly compare theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a common-weale, to a looſe tooth in a mans head, which is both troubleſome and vſeleſſe. Or if you will, they are like <hi>Ants</hi> vpon a mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2806:39"/> which buſie themſelues in a needleſſe and vnprofitable action: and indeed theſe are the very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and incendiaries of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world: all their labour is to handle the ſores of others; &amp; they take as much delight in reproofe, as the <hi>Carter</hi> doth in his whip, who is neuer well, but when hee heares, the laſh. Their words burne in their mindes, as an vnthrifts mony in his purſe: and like an arrow in a dogs ſide, they are neuer well till they are out. Theſe may fitly bee reſembled vnto a cloud, which being poſſeſſed with hot exhalations, is ſo weak that it cannot containe them: and ſo they breake forth to the terrour of the world. Thus, this kinde of people, through the weakneſſe of their minds, &amp; imbecillity of gouerment can keepe nothing that is in their heart, but like <hi>Solomons</hi> foole, <hi>they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>vtter all that is in their minde;</hi> though it bee to the miſchiefe and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2806:39"/> deſtruction of them that liue by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, according to that of <hi>Solomon. An</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11 9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>In o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e hypocro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta corrump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalem ſuum.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 12. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Hypocrite with his mouth deſtroyeth his neighbour:</hi> yea oftentimes wee ſhall finde that men of affinity, and neere acquaintance, will much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate in this kinde. <hi>Ieremic</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of this treachery in his time; and ſo doth the <hi>Prophet David. It was not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>mine enimie that reproached me, then I could haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 55. v 12 13.</note> 
                  <hi>borne it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither was it he that hated me that did magnifie himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, then I would haue hid my face from him. But it was thou O man, mine equall, my guide and mine acquaintance.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> in another place, compares ſuch kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>Bees,</hi> now a <hi>Bee</hi> we know hath hony in her mouth, and a ſting in her taile: we ſhall ſee them come to vs with a ſuperſiciall and outward ſhow of vnfained loue, with as great a complement, as if they would at once proſtrate their ſoules &amp; bodies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2806:40"/> to our good and welfare. And the words of <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Amaſa</hi> ſhall bee at their tongues end, <hi>Quomodo vales?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 20. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Art thou in health my brother?</hi> And yet miſchiefe is in the heart; &amp; they can no more hold their tongues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he his hands, though it bee to the <note place="margin">Pſal. 28. 3.</note> wounding &amp; deſtruction of a man. Now the beſt way to deale with ſuch impoſtors is, to anſwer them as the ſicke <hi>Hen</hi> in the <hi>Fable</hi> anſwered the <hi>Cat,</hi> who asking how ſhe did, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied againe, better if you were far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off from me: better it is to want ſuch friends, then to be betrayed by their pretended friendſhip. Or at leaſt it is good to put no truſt in a friend, nor confidence in a counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: wee liue in the worſt times, in the laſt part of <hi>Nebuchadnezars Image,</hi> the feet whereof are conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of iron and clay, the laſt times of the world, wherein men are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with vnnaturall, iron and ſtonie hearts. <hi>So that they ſhall betray one</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:2806:40"/> 
                  <hi>another and hate one another. The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 10,</note> 
                  <hi>father ſhall bee diuided againſt the ſonne, and the ſonne against the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12 53.</note> 
                  <hi>the mother against the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the daughter againſt the mother: the mother in law againſt the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in law, and the daughter in law againſt the mother in law.</hi> Now where there is this want of a good nature, there wee ſhall finde the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friendly looſeneſſe of trecherous tongues, which is abominated of God and man: and though wee finde ſome, and the moſt, to haue as long eares, as they haue wide <note place="margin">Auriculas Mid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quis non habet? Per. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> mouthes; yet withall wee may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that ſuch men are generally hated, and as ſome loue treaſon, yet all hate the traytour, ſo many will deſire to heare of the faults of others yet withall they will hate the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the relator. Therefore wee are aduiſed not to declare other mens faults, <hi>neither to friend nor foe, end if the ſinne appertaine not</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2806:41"/> 
                  <hi>vnto thee, reveale it not, for hee will harken vnto thee, and marke thee, &amp; when he findeth opportunity he will hate thee: if thou haſt heard a word</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eecl. 19. 8. 9. Eccl. 25. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt thy neighbour let it die with thee:</hi> for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>He that couereth a tranſgreſsion keepeth loue but he that repeateth a matter ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 17. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>very friends,</hi> and it is better with S. <hi>Paul, to ſtudy to be quiet, and to doe our owne buſineſſe.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. 11.</note> relations of others ſhall be told vnto vs, not to bee like <hi>Malchus</hi> without <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 10.</note> the right care, and onely heare with a ſiniſter and left eare, with a crui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and hypocriticall eare. But let vs eare as little to heare ſuch aſperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as wee will to heare the clocke, when wee care not for the houre: then ſhal we obtaine fauour of God and man, and retaine quietneſſe and tranquility in our own ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſe the third.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the laſt cauſe of this vnkinde <note place="margin">The third cauſe is Envy.</note> and diſcourteous reproofe, is <hi>Envy</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:2806:41"/> and <hi>Malice,</hi> which maketh men like fiery <hi>Salamanders,</hi> and raging <hi>Seas</hi> towards their neighbours: they reproue to bring men into diſgrace and ignominie: their end is not to heale the ſore, but to vncouer the wound, and to leaue an vnſighty ſcarre of diſcredit behinde them: &amp; ſometimes they drawe at nothing but ſound and ſolid fleſh: &amp; inſteed of pulling out the more from their brothers eye, they pull out the eye it ſelfe; or if by chance they doe any good, with <hi>Belzebub</hi> they caſt out <hi>Diuells</hi> through the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells.</hi> They behaue themſelues as if they had dranke of <hi>Marah, Maſſah</hi> and <hi>Meribah</hi> bitter waters, or as <note place="margin">Exod. 15 23. Exod. 17. 7.</note> though they had filled themſelues with the waters of ſtrife, as <hi>Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth</hi> with <hi>Iordan:</hi> yea they carry themſelues with ſuch a <hi>Cythian</hi> and barbarous auſterity, as if they were hewen out of <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> &amp; were nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with the milke of <hi>Tygres:</hi> that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2806:42"/> a man may as ſoone get water out of a flint, or oyle out of a ſtony rock, as mild and curteous words from their mouths. Theſe are borne of the curſed ſeed of <hi>Cham,</hi> delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing ſo much as to vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the nakedneſſe of others: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Gen 9. 22.</note> indeed borne of the <hi>Divell</hi> him ſelfe, whoſe name is <hi>Diabolus,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famer, as the word in the <hi>Syriacke</hi> tongue, in S. <hi>Mathewes Goſpell</hi> doth import, expreſſed by the word <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgator,</hi> a publiſher of infamous reports; ſo that hee which lightly conceiues a reproach againſt his neighbour, either for giuing it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by miſconſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, or credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly receauing it vpon the report of others, is nothing elſe but a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> in <hi>Syrtacke.</hi> And therefore S. <note place="margin">2. Tim 3 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>crim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>natores.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, <hi>that in the last times there ſhall be men Diuells falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, euill and reproachfull ſpeakers.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 3. 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>detra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>entes.</hi>
                  </note> And in another place hee ſpeaketh of <hi>women diuells</hi> in regard of their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2806:42"/> ſlanders and detractions. Whereby he ſhewes the neere vnion betwixt a calumnious reprouer and the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell,</hi> for as the <hi>Diuell</hi> by his accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of man to God ſtriues to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowe all his happineſſe; ſo theſe men by ſlanderous aſpertions and accuſations (being as powerfull in them, as the blaſts of Rammes hornes before the walls of <hi>Ierico)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> doe ſtriue to lay all the power and ſtrength of other mens vertues le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell and euen with the ground at one vtterance, and by their bitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling putrifie the ſweet ointment of a mans good name. Yea the good <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 1. Eccl 7 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> name of a man, which is <hi>better then pretious ointment.</hi> Thus they proue moſt malignant and vnluckey Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets to their neighbours where they liue; ſo that a man may with more ſafety play at the hole of an <hi>Aſpe,</hi> and handle a <hi>Cockatrice,</hi> then fall in to the hands of theſe men: whom I take to bee the vncleaneſt <hi>Leapers</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2806:43"/> that euer ſore ranne vpon, moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thily deſeruing the vſage of <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> who were ſewd vp in to a male of leather, and caſt into the Sea, ſo that neither water nor ayre, nor element of any other kind could once approach vnto them. Yea I ſay, they are moſt vnworthy to liue, moue, or haue their beings. Theſe are the ſonnes of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badon,</hi> yea a brutiſh ſpurious and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate ofſpring, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> reports to haue <hi>no faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their mouth, their inward part is very wickednes: their throat</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>is an open ſepulchre,</hi> from whence comes this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rotten ſpeech, aſcending from an internall putrifaction. The beſt way for vs to reproue ſuch reprouers, is to ſay to them as <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lentulus</hi> when hee had vttered his ſtomacke in his face. <hi>Lentulus</hi> they are deceiued that think thou haſt no mouth. And <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen de ira l</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 38.</note> with faire and gentle words to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2806:43"/> them if we can. For in this caſe ſometimes (as the old prouerbe is) it's good to pleaſe a knaue: and to doe to him as <hi>Aeneas</hi> to <hi>Cerberus,</hi> who is reported to caſt a ſweet mor fell to that <hi>Hell-hound,</hi> becauſe hee ſhould not barke at him. Here it is good not to giue <hi>Quid pro quo,</hi> ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for rayling, and rebuke for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, to theſe curſing Shimei's, and dead dogges, leaſt the ſtorme of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in an enimie, and the waues of diſcontent in our own ſelues, doe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Serm.</hi> 3. <hi>in feſt. Epiph.</hi>
                  </note> ſo toſſe the ſhip of our ſoules, that it daſh vpon a rocke, and ſo be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Alſo when wee our ſelues are to reproue any, let vs doe it with the <note place="margin">At pater vt gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, ſic nos debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus amici, ſi quod ſit vttium non faſtidire, Hor.</note> greateſt clemency wee can inuent, with a friendly, brotherly, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection, free from a peeuiſh and enuious diſdaine; handling the ſores of others, as if they were our owne, with as Chriſtian and <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> compaſſion as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>who is weake, and I am not weake? Who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11. 29.</note>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:2806:44"/> 
                  <hi>is offended, and I burne not?</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pitty in our eyes and hearts, when we chance to ſee the falls and infirmities of others. As our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt</hi> who in compaſſion to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> is ſaid <hi>to weepe ouer it.</hi> Let vs bee like <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> who would <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 41. <hi>Qui iuſtis ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciis illa chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>it etiam &amp; jugemuit.</hi>
                  </note> weepe and groane at neceſſary exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of law. Yea let vs imitate a wiſe and mercifull <hi>Chirurgian,</hi> who ſetteth and reſtoreth a limme diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, to his proper place, with as little paine as may bee to the party. Let <hi>Tygers</hi> in the forreſt bee cruell towards their companions, let them bite and be bitten, devoure and bee devoured of one another, let <hi>dogges</hi> grinne, and <hi>Vnicornes</hi> puſh with their hornes; let <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibals</hi> bee cruell and eat the fleſh of men. Let <hi>Midianites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtins</hi> ſheath their ſwords in the bowells <note place="margin">Iudg 7. 22.</note> of each other. Let them forget the loue of the Lord, that the God of heauen may forget his mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2806:44"/> them; let ſuch reprobate mindes carry to their graues, and to that bottomleſſe <hi>Abyſſe</hi> of hell and confuſion, that marke and character of euerlaſting reprobation, that the ſpirit of God hath engrauen vpon their browes and foreheads, that they are falſe accuſing diuels, and men of a fierce and ſauage diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but let euery one of vs that beares any part of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds heauenly image, <hi>who is Father of mercy, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 6. 2. Cor. 1. 3. Eph. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Prince of peace, and rich in mercy vnto vs, be like minded to others, &amp; giue mercy for mercy, grace for grace patience and long ſuffering, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of brotherly kindneſſe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things in charity, and let vs put on as the elect of God, holy and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16. 14. Eph. 4. 31. Col. 3. 12. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>beloued, bowels of mercy, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekeneſse, long ſuffering, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiuing one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Three arguments to moue vs to clemency.</head>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2806:45"/>
                  <p>Now for the better ſtirring vs vp <note place="margin">Three argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to moue vs to gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> to mercy and gentleneſſe in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, let vs conſider three things, Firſt let vs ſearch into the good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> parts of the party offending. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly conſider mans tractable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to good words, and withall his auerſeneſſe to bitter ſpeeches. Thirdly let vs looke vnto our ſelues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> what faults wee haue committed, what wee doe, and what wee may commit: &amp; theſe cannot but moue vs in meekneſſe of carriage towards others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt Argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt let vs conſider with our <note place="margin">1 Argument is the virtue of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> ſelues, what good parts and vertues we can finde in him that hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and let thoſe moue vs to cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, conſidering that there is no gold but hath ſome droſſe, and the beſt men haue their faults. For as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne diuine ſaith, euery one is once a foole, &amp; doth that perhaps in one fit of his folly, which hee ſhall haue
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2806:45"/> leaſure to repent of, as <hi>Noah</hi> in one <note place="margin">Gen. 9 21.</note> houres drunkeneſſe vncouered thoſe ſecrets, which were hid ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before, the world is herevpon ready to call in queſtion all his former integrity, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him out of the hope of any further amendment. But ſeeing God hath giuen vs two eyes, the one ſhould be buſied about the preſent fault that we ſee, with a deteſting commiſeration, the other about the commendable qualities of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: ſince the heart hath no window made to looke into it by the Creator thereof, but is reſerued vnder locke and key for his owne view: I had rather wrong my ſelfe by credulitie, then others by vniuſt cenſures and ſuſpitions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Second argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly conſider mans propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie <note place="margin">2ly Mans pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſitie to good words, <hi>&amp; contra.</hi>
                     </note> to good wordes, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition to rough ſpeeches; the minde of man is naturally ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2806:46"/> and rather followeth with willingneſſe then will bee led by <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Natura contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>max eſt, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>us, quam ducitur. Sen. de cle. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Nullum animal eſt morotius ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, quod<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> arte ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>re tractari debet. Sen. de clem. Tritum eſt illud: Generoſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eſt hominus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, magis du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur quam tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>itur.</hi>
                     </note> harſh meanes, and a minde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighed with the violence of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will ſcarce admit the freedome of reproofe which reaſon might warrant. For there is no creature more waiward then man, nor which ought to be handled with more art, and wee ſhall finde reproofe like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>ſtorme</hi> in the <hi>Fable;</hi> if it be milde and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, like the <hi>Sunne Beames,</hi> it makes a man caſt off his cloake; but if it be turbulent &amp; ſtormic, it cauſeth him to wrap it more cloſe about him, a gentle and louing reproofe makes a man caſt away his tranſgreſſion, but <note place="margin">Plus ita<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit amica cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptio, quam turbulenta ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatio. Amb.</note> violent &amp; tempeſtuous words cauſe him more to cleaue to ſinne: for when a ſweete and louely nature is wildly handled, it makes a man not only to hate and deteſt the <hi>Satyre;</hi> but by accident, it poſſeſſeth the mind, with a more fierie and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2806:46"/> diſpoſition, then that which comes by nature, and this kind of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, was a <hi>Remora</hi> or let to the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians,</hi> whereby they were rather prouoked and ſtirred vp to hatred and enuy, to ſnarling and biting <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1. <hi>Hinc antem non emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves. ſed magis ad odia &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidiam, &amp; ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>emo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dendum prouocabantur. Muſc. in loc.</hi>
                     </note> at the reprouer, then to be bettered by reprehenſions and reproofe, and we ſhall finde it farre better to vſe curteous and gentle perſwaſions, then to enforce by bad language &amp; ill tearmes; for a ſeruile and violent conſtraint exaſperates free ſpirits, and like <hi>Sampſons foxes ſets all on</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iudg 15 4. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>fire,</hi> and maketh ſuch as would bee reclaimed with the violence of ſweete and ſeaſonable words, euen to caſt away ſhame, and perſeuere in faultes. Therefore if euer wee make account to benefit any by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, let vs roote out theſe fibras, and rootes of bitterneſſe, and plante the hearbe <hi>Philantropos,</hi> or <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plin. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt. nat. lib.</hi> 24 <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> brotherly loue in our heartes, then may wee ſtay our mindes with a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2806:47"/> 
                     <hi>good perſwaſion to better the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Third argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly if the two former will <note place="margin">3 Argument is to conſider our ſelues.</note> not perſwade to milde &amp; gentle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, then let vs conſider our own weakneſſe, calling to mind what wee haue beene, what wee are and what we may be.</p>
                  <p>Firſt let vs conſider what wee <note place="margin">1 What wee haue beene.</note> were and haue beene. This S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> would haue <hi>Titus</hi> to put his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in mind of, that they ſhould ſpeake euill of no man, that <hi>they ſhould bee no brawlers; but gentle,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 2. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhewing all meekeneſſe vnto all men, For (ſaith he) wee our ſelues were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, ſeruing diuerſe luſts &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, we were once without Chriſt, and aliants from the common-wealth</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>of Iſrael, and were ſtrangers from the couenant of promiſe, and had no hope, and were without God in the world.</hi> Once likewiſe we were babes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2806:47"/> and weake in grace, and in the heat of youth; and had much trouble &amp; difficultie, in encountring and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the vanitie of that age; &amp; there was leſſe probabilitie in vs of that good wee haue, then in them wee reproue, for which cauſe we haue no more reaſon, in a bitter reproofe, to vaunt our ſelues ouer our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, then the wall whereon the ſun ſhines, (though it ſelfe baſe) ſhould contemne the <hi>marble</hi> wall, becauſe it is in ſome obſcure place where the <hi>Sunne</hi> is not ſo powerfull: though in proceſſe of time it may receiue more light and influence from the ſunne then that doth. Take wee heed then, in our reproofe, wee haue reſpect to what we were at firſt our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and what the reprooued may come to, for otherwiſe, if wee haue not a care, hee ſhall bee our iudge in concluſion, who at firſt was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nobis erit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex, qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>it ante nobis reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d what wee are.</note> to vs, and to our reprehenſion.</p>
                  <p>Secondly let vs weigh with our
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2806:48"/> ſelues what we are for time preſent, namely ſo weak as not able to ſtand one hower by our owne ſtrength &amp; abilitie; but as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>By the grace of God I am that I am,</hi> &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee ſhall finde more cauſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 18. <hi>Qui ſeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>. ſum a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>cit, non quarit, quid in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> frequenter reprehendat: ſed in ſemetipſo quid l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ter:</hi>
                     </note> wailing our owne ſinnes, then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to controll the faults of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we haue more need to breake open the ſteele gates of our owne breaſts, wherein our ſinnes lie hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, then violently to ruſh into the coffers of other mens infirmities: and to conſider with our ſelues what ſinnes wee haue of late mortified, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quod malum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>odie ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>afli. Sen, de ira lib.</hi> 3.</note> before we ſtrike our neighbour vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently on the face, leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be ſaid to vs as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> to <hi>Ioh, Behold thou haſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 4. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>taught many, and ſtrengthened the weary handes: thy words haue infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him that was falling, and thou hast vpheld the weake knees: but now it is come vpon thee, and thou art grieued, it toucheth thee and thou art troubled,</hi> and let vs ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2806:48"/> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Sirs, Why doe yee theſe things? We alſo are men of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Act. 14. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>like paſsions with you,</hi> for there is no man liuing that can ſay of himſelfe as our <hi>Sauiour Christ, Which of you</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 46.</note> 
                     <hi>conuinceth me of ſinne?</hi> But if there bee any man, that in his owne eyes ſeemes thus holy, <hi>let him caſt the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>firſt ſtone at him that ſinneth.</hi> How vnnaturall then doe thoſe deale, which beholding ſo much the faults of others, forgette their owne frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and humane nature. What? are <note place="margin">Et quid ſunt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> illi iudices? an non homines &amp; ipſi. Muſc.</note> they not men as well as others? If they will bee men and not beaſts, how vnhumane are they, who think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they can neuer ſufficiently ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate the ſinnes of others, forget their owne tranſgreſſions? or if they <note place="margin">Puluere ſi le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſcribunt, ſed marmore laſi.</note> doe remember them, write their owne in the duſt, and others in marble.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly and laſtly, let vs conſider <note place="margin">3 What we may be.</note> what wee our ſelues may fall into. <hi>Conſider thy ſelfe leaſt thou alſo bee</hi>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2806:49"/> 
                     <hi>tempted,</hi> this good vſe did a <hi>Father</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1.</note> make of another mans fall. He hath fallen this day, &amp; I not vnlike to fall to morrow. And in another place he aduiſeth vs not in any caſe to iudge <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ille hodie &amp; ego eras. Ber. Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>de reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Dom. Non iudicos fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem magis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem excuſa: excuſa intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſi opus non potes, puta ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iam, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſubr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ptionem, puta caſum; Deoaſi omnem omnino diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> rel certitude recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat, ſuade ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilominus ipſe tibi, &amp; dicito a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud teipſum, vehemeni fuit nimis tentatio. Quid de me illa feciſſet, ſi acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſet in me ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Ber. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Cant.</hi>
                     </note> our brother, but rather, if wee canue to excuſe him any way; but if wee can no way excuſe him, (as he large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aduiſeth) then he would haue vs conſider what ſuch a temptation as our neighbours was, would haue wrought vpon vs, if it had had the like power againſt vs. Thus let vs when wee chance to ſee other mens infirmities, behold our owne faults, as when wee looke into the apple of another mans eye, wee may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our owne eyes. But herein many may be taxed, who neuer grow into conſideration with themſelues how they may be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſo that ſometimes it falleth out, that for their vnmercifulneſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, God giues them ouer to the ſhame of the ſame ſinne themſelues.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2806:49"/> Others there are (and ſometimes good men) who will ſtrictly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that which themſelues fall into. Thus it was with <hi>Dauid,</hi> who when <hi>Nathan</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation vnto him of one that had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away a poore mans lambe, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids anger was greatly kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>the man, and he ſaid to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, As the Lord liueth the man that hath done this thing ſhall ſurely dye.</hi> But when <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to him thou art the man, then he was both aſhamed and ſilent. Thus <hi>Iuda</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Thamar</hi> had played the harlot, preſently cries out, bring her forth and let her be burnt, but when ſhe ſhewed vnto him, the <hi>Signets</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 28. 25. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and Bracelets &amp; the ſtaffe,</hi> as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his owne abomination &amp; filthineſſe, then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e could not but confeſſe, that ſhe whom he ſo raſhly had condemned, <hi>was more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then himſelfe.</hi> Thus when men haue heard relation of the faults of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2806:50"/> others, and the odiouſneſſe of the ſame, they are ready on a ſudden, to condemne them to the greateſt iudgement they can thinke of; but when the ſame imperſections are laid to their owne charge, then they grow more remiſſe and mercifull, yea good men I ſay, oftentimes ſpare themſelues in great offences, whereas trifles in others ſhall haue <hi>Summumius.</hi> Extreame right, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame wrong, and though ſome times like the <hi>moone</hi> they are full of blots and imperfections, yet (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prouerbe) they will looke beyond the <hi>moone,</hi> and complaine againſt the leaſt moat they behold in the <hi>Sunne,</hi> yea wee ſhall finde the moſt wicked men that liue, like barren rocks and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, complaine of a fruitfull and fertile ſoyle, becauſe here and there ſpringes vp a thiſtle and a weed, and the cauſe is, men are giuen more to ſee into the faultes of others, then
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2806:50"/> their owne. For euery man (ſaith <hi>Aeſop)</hi> hath a <hi>wallet</hi> hanging vpon his ſhoulders; the one halfe hanges vpon our breaſt, and the other halfe vpon our backe: the former is full of other mens faults, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually behold: that part which is behinde, and loaden with our owne offences, wee neuer regard, nor caſt an eye towards it, &amp; by this meanes wee become vnmercifull towards others, &amp; too ſparing to our ſelues. Therefore to moue vs to pittie and commiſeration in our reproofes to our brethren, let vs conſider that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Aut ſumus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> vel poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> eſſe quod hic eſt.</note> wee haue beene, are, or may bee as bad as they that ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third circumſtance in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of reprouing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the third and laſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <note place="margin">3 Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing is Courage.</note> to be conſidered in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of reproofe is <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie;</hi> as well as wiſdome, and gentleneſſe, we muſt haue the <hi>Oare</hi> of loue and the <hi>Oare</hi> of feare to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2806:51"/> worke in the delinquent, by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall <note place="margin">Remum am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ris &amp; remum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris. Plut.</note> courage, of a wiſe reprouer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Herein wee muſt be like the <hi>Bee,</hi> which is not all hony, it hath a ſting alſo, and our reproofe muſt be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered according to the riddle of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fortiter ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> Iudg. 14 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Sampſon;</hi> both ſtrong in ſweetneſſe, and ſeet in ſtrength, otherwiſe we ſhall finde but little profit redownd to our labours, for although loue &amp; faire meanes winne and recall ſome: yet there are others that wee muſt <note place="margin">Iude. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaue with feare pulling them out of the fire,</hi> theſe muſt bee handled roughly (as <hi>Hagar</hi> was) for as all men ſleepe not alike, ſo neither are <note place="margin">Prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cero <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ducere verbera.</note> they to be wakened alike, to ſome we muſt giue the breaſt, to others the rodde; otherwiſe by ſparing we ſpill.</p>
                  <p>Our <hi>Courage</hi> muſt conſiſt in two <note place="margin">Two things to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in courage</note> things, Frſt that we ſpare to reproue the perſon of no man, when we haue authority to reproue. Secondly that we let paſſe no ſin in the party reproued.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:2806:51"/>
                  <p>Firſt we muſt ſhew our true zeale <note place="margin">1 Property of courage.</note> and courage in reprouing whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee ſee ſinne. Herein we are bound to ſay as <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid. Thou art the man, as Elias to Ahab,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12 7. 1 Kings 18. 18. 2 Chr. 26. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>It is thou and thy fathers houſe that trouble Iſrael. Azaria rebuked vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah. It partaineth not to thee to burne incenſe. Aſa</hi> reproued his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <note place="margin">1 King. 15. 13.</note> Yea wee muſt reproue <hi>Father</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 14 26.</note> 
                     <hi>and Mother, and wife, and children and brethren and ſiſters,</hi> be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo deare, or neere vnto vs by the bonds of loue or relation. Let vs not doe as many puſillanimous &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate ſpirits, who dare aduenture to check an inferior, but to a man in power they dare not ſay as <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist to Herod, it is not lawfull for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 14. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>thee,</hi> they will aduenture perhaps to throw a ſtone at a <hi>Dogge,</hi> but to looke but a <hi>Lyon</hi> in the face they dare not. Some againe will not ſticke to bee couragious in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, but their rebuke ſhall fall rather
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2806:52"/> vpon vertue then vpon vice; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dat veniam cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cenſura colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas lunen. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.</hi> 1</note> and ſo reproue where they ſhould cheriſh &amp; maintaine, this is as met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell in a blind horſe, &amp; doth endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger both his owne life, and the life of him who ſhould be his guide. It is neceſſary that our reproofe ſhould be ſetled vpon a right obiect, and then let it be in vs as powder to the bullet, to offer violence vpon the face of any ſinner, and like the flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſword in the <hi>Cherubims</hi> hand to keepe him from forbidden fruit. Though a ſinner ſwell with pride &amp; contempt, as <hi>Behemoth</hi> with <hi>Iordan;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 40. 23.</note> if he be <hi>Agag</hi> let him ſuffer as well as the pooreſt <hi>Amalakite.</hi> Let vs not ſticke to touch the hole of the <hi>Aſpe;</hi> and to lay our handes vpon the den of the <hi>Cockatrice;</hi> then ſhall wee ſhew our true valour indeed, euery coward dares ſet his foot vpon a poore ſilly worm, becauſe it hath no power to reſiſt, but hee is the beſt man that dares encounter where
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2806:52"/> greateſt oppoſition is.</p>
                  <p>Secondly as wee muſt know our <note place="margin">2 Property of true courage.</note> courage in ſparing the perſon of no man, ſo likewiſe in ſparing the ſinne of no perſon, we muſt deale as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates their ſinne to them. <hi>It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>commonly that there is forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation amongſt you:</hi> wee muſt deale with our friends as the <hi>Painter</hi> dealt with <hi>Alexander,</hi> who painted him out curiouſly, yet with his ſcarre in his face, and <hi>Clitus</hi> that loued him beſt, condemned and reproued his quaffing, (though for the manner he did it ſo vnaduiſedly as it coſt him his life). Thus muſt we ſpare no ſinne wee ſee in others, but diſcouer and make it manifeſt: Imitating the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full painter, who ſhadoweth a man in all his partes, and giueth euery peece his iuſt proportion: thus in our reproofe we muſt decipher out, and ſhew euery humour in the kinde: &amp; as the <hi>Chirurgion</hi> that maketh the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2806:53"/> 
                     <hi>Anatomie,</hi> ſheweth as well the <hi>muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> in the heele, as the veines in the heart. So in our reprouing, we muſt faithfully and fully ſet downe the faultes of the party offending, that he may both ſee them and ſhunne them. <hi>Let vs not bee fearefull to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>men,</hi> whoſe breath is in his noſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills, but let vs <hi>feare God, who is able to cast both ſoule and body into hell fire,</hi> leaſt (according to the old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe) whileſt we feare the froſt, we be ouerwhelmed with the ſnow <hi>for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Qui time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>am, irruet ſuper eos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ix.</hi> Prov. 29. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>as Solomon ſaith. The feare of man bringeth a ſnare, but who ſo puteth his truſt in the Lord, ſhall be ſafe.</hi> Here then are all ſuch to bee reproued who want courage in this chriſtian duty Eſpecially <hi>Ministers</hi> &amp; <hi>Magiſtrats</hi> who haue moſt authority to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. It is a ſhame to ſee a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ſtand like <hi>Harpocrates</hi> the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian God,</hi> with his fingers in his mouth when <hi>Babel</hi> is building, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2806:53"/> ſinne reacheth vp to the heauens. Shame it is that the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ſhould not be ſuch a man, as <hi>Iethro</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21.</note> counſelled <hi>Moſes</hi> to make choice of; <hi>a man of courage, fearing God,</hi> and <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> whereas he is ſtiled <hi>Goas ſword bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, not to weare it</hi> for a ſhew and for nought, hee doth not execute wrath vpon him that doth evill, but lets all runne at <hi>Randum,</hi> which way it will. Or if he doth any thing, there is no more life in his actions then in a child that is ſtill borne. Yea the <hi>Minister</hi> that ſhould fight with the ſword of their ſpirit, and the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> with the ſword of iuſtice, both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let the ſword lye, as the ſword of <hi>Goliah</hi> ruſting behinde the <hi>Ephod:</hi> and like the <hi>Sword-fiſh,</hi> they <note place="margin">1. Sam. 21. 9.</note> haue a ſword but no heart; or like a cowardly <hi>Gallant,</hi> they carry a ſword about them, but dare not drawe it, though their cauſe bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good and honeſt. Let me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe therefore both <hi>Miniſter</hi> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2806:54"/> 
                     <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to put on courage as a garment vpon them, and though they ſhould bee much oppoſed by ſinne and ſinfull men, yet let them with the <hi>Horſe</hi> neigh at the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and with the <hi>Leviathan</hi> laugh at the ſpeare, and make difficulties whetſtones to fortitude, let them conioyne and vnite their forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſay to one another as <hi>Ioab to Abiſhai. If the Aſſyrians be too ſtrong for me, then thou ſhalt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Chro. 19. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>helpe me: but if the children of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be too ſtrong for thee, then I will helpe thee.</hi> Euen ſo if an army of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall affront either <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or <hi>Miniſter,</hi> let them conioine their power and courage, to the cutting downe all monſtrous and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous outrages: then ſhall we ſee that ſinne will not ſo abound amongſt many, and the iudgement of God ſhall be preuented fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling down vpon vs all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:2806:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>Inſtruction the firſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw in the third place, if the doctrine of reproofe bee ſo <note place="margin">1 Inſtruction is to keep our ſelues from reproofe.</note> neceſſary and profitable. This ſhould teach vs that leſſon of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to keep our ſelues <hi>blameleſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and harmeleſse, the ſonnes of God without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked &amp; perverſe nation, amongſt whom wee ſhine as lights in the world.</hi> And though we cannot but conuerſe with ſinners, and be behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the ſinnes of others, yet let vs haue a care, that wee bee not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with their euill manners. Let vs be like the bird <hi>Trochilus,</hi> that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in the mouth of the <hi>Crocodile</hi> and is not ſpoiled: like the <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> that lies in the fire, and is not
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2806:55"/> burnt, or like fiſh that liue and ſwim in the ſalt ſea, and yet taſt not of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Piſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>i &amp; alii, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem tamem non reſerunt. Lipſ. conſtant: lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16 1 Ioh. 2. 20. 27.</note> ſalt. And the rather becauſe as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, wee haue receaued <hi>the vnction of the ſpirit,</hi> now oyle though it bee powred into other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, yet it ſwimmes on the top, &amp; keepes it ſelfe vnmixed. So though wee cannot but mix our ſelues with the world in naturall actions, yet in ſpiritual affaires let vs ſtriue alwaies to ſwimme aloft, leaſt the wicked ones of this world (like curſed <hi>Cham)</hi> behold our nakedneſſe, and ſport themſelues at our ſhame: for <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 22.</note> we ſhall finde them to make a ſmall fault in a profeſſor to exceed in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe the greateſt of their owne. And ſo that ſinne which was not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of before a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, will proue a great diſgrace and ignominie to him, in time of his good conuerſation. For as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a comely and delectable picture &amp; portraiture be cut or drawne out, it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2806:55"/> mattereth not much how vneuen &amp; knotty the bord be, wherevpon it is to be drawne; but when once the picture is finiſhed and brought to perfection, then the leaſt knot or blemiſh will ſeeme a great deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and diſgrace to the picture. In like manner, though it bee not of ſo great importance and obſeruation, our follies and errours committed in the old man: yet ſeeing God hath wrought the ſacred impreſſion of his holy ſpirit in out hearts, if wee walke inordinately now, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law of God, the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer blemiſhes and imperfections of our ſoules wil proue more diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and odious in the eies of the world, in regard wee haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed <hi>Chaos</hi> of nature in vs, transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the image of God. But to keepe mee to my mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand; the beſt and ſafeſt way to keepe vs both from the ſinnes of others, and from the aſpertion of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2806:56"/> the world, will bee to haue nothing to doe with the men nor their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but rather to take the counſell of <hi>Solomon, Enter not into the path of the wicked, and goe not in the way</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of evill men.</hi> I might lay downe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons why wee ſhould neither <hi>walke,</hi> nor <hi>ſtand,</hi> not <hi>ſit</hi> with wicked <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 1.</note> men. But theſe few arguments may moue vs.</p>
               <p>Firſt ſuch as wee commonly and frequently haue ſociety with, ſuch <note place="margin">1 Argument to diſſwade vs from ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note> commonly we are our ſelues: there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ordinarily to aſſociate with wicked men, is a ſigne of a wicked diſpoſition. And therefore the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians</hi> that they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtand the quality and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of their children, were wont to enquire what companions they linked themſelues withall. And this vſe of company and acquaintance did <hi>Auguſtus</hi> make, who being at <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> a Combate, where there was a great company of people, amongſt the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2806:56"/> reſt, his two daughters <hi>Iulia</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> were preſent; who therevpon tooke occaſion to marke what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany reſorted to them, to court and ſalute them: and ſeeing that graue <hi>Senators</hi> talked with <hi>Livia,</hi> &amp; looſe <note place="margin">Dulcè quidem dulci ſe adiunx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maris.</note> ſtriplings, and riotous perſons with <hi>Iulia:</hi> hee therevpon knew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions &amp; inclinations of his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Thus may we take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſo long as a man doth com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly &amp; frequently with a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <note place="margin">Qui aequo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo malis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcetur, malus eſt.</note> of minde haunt the company of wicked men, that he is ſuch a one himſelfe. Therefore let vs reſolue with <hi>David, not to ſit with vaine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 26.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>perſons, nor to abide with diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers.</hi> Neither let vs bee partakers with them; <hi>for though we were ſome times darkneſſe, yet now we are light</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>in the Lord: let vs therefore walke as children of the light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly keeping company with <note place="margin">2 Argument to diſſwade vs from ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note> wicked men, doth not onely giue a man his denomination: but likewiſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2806:57"/> it doth by a ſecret infuſion of ſinne, wonderfully infect the ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And hee that aſſociateth with euill men muſt needs <hi>learne their wayes.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 25.</note> Sinne amongſt men is like the rot amongſt ſheepe, its catching and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious. If wee ſleepe with dogges wee ſhall bee ſure to ſwarme with fleas, if we fly with <hi>Ostridges</hi> and <hi>Pelicans</hi> wee cannot but haue a tincture of their wild nature, and like <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſheepe, wee ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <note place="margin">Gen. 30. 38. 39</note> and bring forth according to the obiects ſet before vs, yea though before wee goe into wicked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, we may reſolue not to partake of their ſinnes; yet the beſt men ſhall finde it as impoſſible to frequent ordinarily euill company, and to returne from them as good as when they went in, as for ſheepe to liue amongſt bryars and thornes, and not to leaue ſome of their woll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, for the beſt men are like wax, as apt to receiue the impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2806:57"/> of ſinne, as that of grace, and as thoſe that goe into the <hi>Sunne</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Sunne burnt, though they goe not for that intent. So they that goe into wicked ſociety, become <note place="margin">Prov. 13. 20. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> natione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi>
                  </note> worſe then they were, euen whileſt they thinke not of it, euen as ſore eyes doe infect the ſound, whileſt we expect no miſchiefe at all. But ſome man may ſay, I may doe good <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> to ſome which are bad, by going into their company; by my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes exhortations and good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. I anſwere; It is a great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> whether thou canſt better the bad, but its ton to one thou keepeſt thy ſelfe from doing any good in meane time, and with <hi>Dauid</hi> thou <note place="margin">Pſal 39 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> muſt refraine <hi>thy tongue from good ſpeech whileſt the wicked are in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> for vngodly men will keepe others from godlineſſe, as the dead <note place="margin">Gen. 8 7.</note> carkaſes did the <hi>Rauen</hi> from <hi>Noahs Arke,</hi> and as the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> cannot draw yron, if the <hi>Diamond</hi> ly by it:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2806:58"/> ſoe neither canne the ſoule of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian be tractable to goodneſſe when ill company are preſent. Let vs not thinke to imitate the <hi>Grafter</hi> who ioynes good fruit to a <hi>Crab-tree.</hi> Nor to be like the <hi>Bee</hi> the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of whoſe nature, makes things of another nature ſweet. Let vs not thinke the life of grace in vs, will make them aliue to goodneſſe, but rather they being dead in ſinne, may kill our vertues. It is written of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zentius</hi> the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> that he ioyned <note place="margin">Corpora corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gebat mortua viuis.</note> dead bodies with the liuing, but the dead did not reuiue by the liuing, but the liuing putrified by the dead. Therefore ſeeing euill company is ſo dangerous and infectious, let vs doe like the <hi>Swallowes</hi> who durſt not come within <hi>Thebes</hi> becauſe the walls were ſo often beſeiged: Let vs not put on winges to fly into ſuch company, whoſe manners proue continuall enimies to our ſoules, but when wee haue to doe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2806:58"/> any thing with them, or by them, let vs doe as the <hi>Egyptian dogges</hi> at the riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> for feare of the <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile</hi> who lap and runne, not mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſtay by them leaſt they ſhould be deuoured. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner let vs be chary how we come into the company of wicked men, leaſt whileſt wee intend to reproue and better them, wee our ſelues are reproued and made worſe.</p>
               <p>And we are bound in duty not only to keepe our ſelues out of the company of euill men, &amp; from their infection; but likewiſe as occaſion ſerues, to condemne and reproue their wicked behauiours; and as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Bee</hi> hath a ſting to rouſe vp the <hi>Drone,</hi> and if any be naſtie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome, to make them mundifie and cleanſe themſelues: So euery Chriſtian muſt haue a tongue to raiſe vp the ſluggard, from his ſinne, for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>The words of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the wiſe are as goades and pricks in</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2806:59"/> 
                  <hi>the ſide of the ſluggard,</hi> therefore let the father deale with his children, the maſter with his ſeruants, &amp; one friend faithfully with another. But ſome man may obiect and ſay, I <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> would willingly reproue ſuch and ſuch a friend, but I know not how he will take it, and ſo happily I may looſe my friend and my labour at once. I anſwere. Neuertheleſſe thou <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> muſt performe thy chriſtian duty, and leaue the euent to God, who hath the hearts of all men in his hands, and can turne them as the waters; and withall let vs conſider the ſaying of <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He that rebuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man, afterwards ſhall finde</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>more fauour, then he that flattereth with the tongue,</hi> beſides if wee ſhould looſe a friend by our wiſe &amp; holy rebukes, wee ſhall bee ſure to finde a friend of God, and howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſhall fall out that the reproued ſhall not take it in as good part, as it is giuen, yet it is better for vs and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2806:59"/> him, that wee ſhould ſuffer his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſpleaſure, then his ſinne and deſtruction. Or if wee can doe him no good by our rebukes, yet wee muſt reproue him: and indeed God requires not at our handes the cure of the partie wee deale with, that muſt bee wrought by his owne hand and mercy; only wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to haue a care ouer one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: <hi>Christ</hi> like the good <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 33. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>an,</hi> requires the ſeeing to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he himſelfe will pay for his coſt, and heale his perſon. Therefore let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man reſolue with that <hi>Heathen Diuine.</hi> I dare make ſo bold, as to <note place="margin">Audeo pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anti mala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, vitia eius ſi non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xcidere, inhibebo Sen.</note> tell a tranſgreſſour of his faults, if I cut not away his vices, I will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding inhibite them. And that our reproofes may the better take impreſſion in the heartes of the reproued it is very requiſite that wee keepe our ſelues vnſported of ſuch ſinnes as we gainſay in others, by which meanes wee ſhall bee ſure
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2806:60"/> to conuince the conſcience of the ſinner, of the errour of his actions, which wee by an holy and heauenly contrariety doe contrary, and indeed this is the beſt reproofe of all, when by a contrariety of carriage wee make manifeſt the ſinnes of others, reforming our ſelues firſt, and then endeauouring the good of others, <note place="margin">Charitas enim ordinata eſſe debet, vt homo prius curam ſui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phus habeat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>einde proximi. Stella.</note> and this is it which God requires of euery reproouer. But alaſſe this courſe is contrary to the carriage of many, who practice themſelues in the reformation of others, but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome looke home to their owne waies: theſe are like vnto ſome of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> who would needs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui cateris praeſtantiores videri velehant cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſent &amp; ipſi carnales, magna ſeuerita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te mordebant ac damnabant eos qui per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitatem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquebans Muſc. in G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ.</hi> 6. 1.</note> ſeeme better then others, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues carnall would with much ſeueritie condemne thoſe which fell meerely of infirmity, theſe men haue eyes with double balls to ſee with, and ſtand out of the head, nearer to other men then to themſelues, ſtaring at faultes
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2806:60"/> committed abroad, but blind as <hi>bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> to behold their owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O maior tandem parcas inſane minori Horat. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Sat.</hi> 3.</note> and ſo they reproue the ſmaller offences of others with greater of their owne, and thus according to the Prouerbe vice corrects ſinne. <note place="margin">Iratos irati ipſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>biurgamu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Plut.</note> Theſe men are like vnto the <hi>Ibis,</hi> a great birde in the cittie of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which was kept only to deuoure the garbage and offall, and to cleanſe the ſtreets, but ſhee left of her owne filth and beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, more noyſome behind her, <note place="margin">Mala mens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> animus.</note> thus many will controll the faylings of others, with greater impurity &amp; impiety of their owne, theſe men ſeldome doe good, but rather hurte to them they reproue, they doe as it were put their durtie fingers to wipe out the moat they behold in the eye of their brother, which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſeth the eye to periſh, then helpes the ſight. Therefore I will ſtriue firſt to caſt out the beame out of mine owne eye, that thereby I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2806:61"/> may more clearely ſee to caſt the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te out of my brothers eye: I will firſt learne to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and forſake mine owne ſinne; before I ſharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue it in another; leaſt that ſpeech of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> bee applied to me as to the <hi>Phariſee, Thou hypocrite firſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 5. Luk. 6. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>caſt out, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Instruction the ſecond.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This alſo in the ſecond place may aduiſe vs to <hi>beare the word of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Inſtruction to ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. Heb. 13. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>and reproofe,</hi> and to endure a memorandum for our miſcarriages, and if a friend ſhall ſtrike vs on the one cheeke with reprehenſion let vs be ſo farre from reſiſting, that wee rather <hi>turne to him the other cheeke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat 9 39.</note> 
                  <hi>alſo.</hi> It was the wiſdome of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> to ſubmit himſelfe to the check of <hi>Nathan,</hi> and to yeeld his necke (as it were) to the blocke for his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: he ſerued not <hi>Nathan</hi> as <hi>Ahab</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 13.</note> ſerued <hi>Eliah,</hi> who held him for the <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> of the land and troubler of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> becauſe hee told him of his <note place="margin">1 King. 18. 17.</note>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:2806:61"/> ſinnes: neither vſed him as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did the <hi>Prophet</hi> of <hi>Iudah,</hi> cauſe his ſeruant to lay hold on him: neither tells him hee is a <hi>Prophet</hi> as well as himſelfe, and therefore <hi>Medice cura teipſum. Phyſitian</hi> heale thy ſelfe; <note place="margin">Luk. 4. 23.</note> but he quietly ſubmits himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cenſure of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and the rod of God, to doe what hee would with him. Thus ought we to behaue our ſelues when wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued: not with wicked and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying Spirits, be more outragious when we are told of our faults; but rather take occaſion thereby to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſelues in goodneſſe: and though in part wee bee in the right way, yet let inſtruction &amp; reproofe be vnto vs, as the winde to a ſhip, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make vs goe faſter though we haue already the tide. Let vs thinke our ſelues more bound to a faithfull friend, that wiſely reproues our faults, then to all the adulterous flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and <hi>Syrens</hi> ſonges, of ſuch as
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2806:62"/> ſhall ſooth vs vp in our iniquities; knowing that the corroſiue which healeth with paine, is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſting of the <hi>Serpent</hi> that killeth with pleaſure. And as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith. <hi>It is better to heare the rebuke of the wiſe, then for a man to heare the ſong</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 7. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>of fooles. Yea open rebuke is better</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 5. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>then ſecret loue, and faithfull are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enimy are deceitfull.</hi> And indeed there is more hope of good, in that man that will take well the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a faithfull friend, then of him who will ſwallow downe the ſuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red words of a perfidious <hi>Paraſite;</hi> who only layes healing plaiſters to the ſore, to skin it aloft, when there is more need of corraſiues to eat out the dead fleſh that is within; thus whilſt their ſpeeches are faire like <hi>Iezabel</hi> vnder painting, and their <note place="margin">2. King. 9. 30.</note> mouthes ſeeme to be full of <hi>Nectar,</hi> yet the gall of bitterneſſe is in their hearts, and they are deceitfull in all
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2806:62"/> their waies. Therefore when our friend ſhall tell vs of our faults, yea though hee doe it with the more ſharpneſſe, yet let vs freely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly beare the ſame, though hec burne our ſore, or lance our wound, <note place="margin">Medicum &amp; vrentem &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantem diliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Amor.</note> yet let vs vndergoe it with patience in our ſelues, and loue to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of our ſoules. Let vs ſtriue to compoſe our minds to a good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility and morigerous tolleration, that no wiſe obiurgation &amp; chiding proue bitter to vs, but thoſe corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which breath humanity and clemency, and ariſe from a placid &amp; beneuolous minde, let vs receiue them louingly and beare them pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, reſoluing with the <hi>Prophet David. Let the righteom ſmite mee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 141. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>it ſhall be kindneſſe, and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue me, it ſhall be an excellent oyle, which ſhall not breake my head.</hi> But <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> ſome man may obiect and ſay, that he that reproues him doth it out of malice, and therefore why ſhould
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2806:63"/> he harken to his reprehenſions? I anſwere, though hee ſhould fayle in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> the manner of reproofe, yet let vs make the beſt vſe we can of it, and though he that reproues, aimes at our diſcredit and ignominie, yet let vs ſtriue to conuert it to our good: as hee that would haue ſmote <hi>Iaſon</hi> to the heart, by accident opened his impoſtume and ſaued his life. Or as <hi>Achilles,</hi> who when hee wounded <note place="margin">Vna eadem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> manus vulnus opem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tulit.</note> 
                  <hi>Telephus,</hi> with the ruſt of that ſpeare which ſhould haue killed him, hee was cured. Thus let vs ſtriue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the miſchieuous end and intent of an enuious reprouer, to the good and converſion of our owne ſoules. And make the malitious aſpertions of our enimies to be as thornes and briers in our way to keepe vs from the forbidden paſtures of iniquity and tranſgreſſion. But ſome man may further obiect and ſay, hee that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> reproues me is as bad as the worſt; and why ſhould I be guided by him
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2806:63"/> that cannot gouerne himſelfe? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere this is a fooliſh &amp; ſimple pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> and excuſe to keepe a mans beloued ſinne; this is as if a man ſhould refuſe ſome ſoueraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, becauſe the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is ſicke of the ſame diſeaſe; how ſimple is that man that will refuſe the phyſick of him that cannot cure himſelfe? Would not the <hi>Lord</hi> haue been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with <hi>Noah,</hi> if hee had wilfully <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 14.</note> reiected his owne ſafety in the <hi>Arke,</hi> becauſe the men that built it were drowned themſelues? And ſhall we reiect the good aduices &amp; reproofs of a friend, or the miniſter of Gods word, becauſe his life is not ſo good as he deſires it and thine? But know thou this whoſoeuer thou art, that though his life be neuer ſo bad, if his reprehenſions be not followed, they will be of ſufficient power, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee at the day of Chriſt, though he that reptoues thee ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not the iſſue of his owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:2806:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reproofe the firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then are to be reproued all <note place="margin">1 Reproofe to ſuch as will not ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke.</note> ſuch as will not beare a reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon faults committed, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light altogether in faire words and flatteries, they make reproofe the only choake-peare they can take, though it be neuer ſo ſeaſonable &amp; iuſt, they are rather exaſperated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reprouer, then amended by reproofe, theſe are like a <hi>Canon</hi> that is ouer charged, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the match is put to it; which will either recoile or burſt, ſo that it proues dangerous to the <hi>Gunner,</hi> if it coſt him not his life: ſo that a man may ſay to them as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Galathians. Am I therefore become your enimie,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe I tell you the truth?</hi> &amp; when we ſhall come to caſt out <hi>Legions</hi> of fowle ſpirits out of their hearts, they will reply, <hi>what haue we to doe with thee, Ieſus th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſonne of the moſt high</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>God?</hi> yea let the reprouer bee <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> or <hi>Miniſter,</hi> they will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2806:64"/> malice as <hi>Ahab;</hi> or pride &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, <hi>yee take too much vpon you.</hi> Or as <note place="margin">Num. 16. 3. Exod. 2. 14. Act. 7. 27.</note> one of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to <hi>Moſes, who made thee a Iudge?</hi> Some goe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Ahab</hi> to impriſon. And ſome with <hi>Herod,</hi> could find in their hearts to cut off <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> head, <note place="margin">Mar. 6. 27.</note> and take away their liues. Yea moſt men we ſhall finde like <hi>Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> wife, who would haue worne <hi>Tullies</hi> tongue in her hat, becauſe he reproued the faults of her husband. Theſe are like the Horſe and Mule, <note place="margin">Pſal. 32 9.</note> without vnderſtanding, let a man feed them all his life time, and no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance is made, but when their kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per comes to let them blood, to drench them, or meddle with their ſores (hauing no reaſon to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend their owne good) they ſtriue to miſchiefe him, that only aimes at their health; and ſome horſes there are againe, which being trauelling, if they be ſpurred, they fling about
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2806:65"/> them rather then mend their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce. Thus wee ſhall finde many behaue themſelues, when they are reproued, tell them of their faults, and ſtriue to reſtore them from the diſtemper of their ſoules, and they wil inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſt, and brutiſhly oppoſe thoſe good motions and exhortations, which tend to the good of their ſoules. For as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith. <hi>He that hateth reproofe is brutiſh.</hi> And <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is grieuous to him that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 12. 1. Prov. 15. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>thy way.</hi> Theſe men deale with them that correct their faults, and ſhew them their imperfections, as the <hi>Ape</hi> with the looking-glaſſe, who beholding therein his ilfauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red face and feature, ſtriues by all meanes to breake the glaſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſeeth himſelfe. A faithfull and wiſe reprouer is like a looking glaſſe wherein a man may ſee his ſpirituall faults and blemiſhes, a diſobedient and ſtubborne heart is like vnto the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pe,</hi> who ſtriues not to mend his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2806:65"/> faults, but labours to breake the glaſſe, that is, to miſchiefe him that laieth his faults ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before his face, and this peruerſneſſe of mind ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many ſoules to hell, <hi>For he that hateth reproofe ſhall dye.</hi> How many <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 1.</note> then ſhall ſhake hands with death and deſtruction, who being great in place, &amp; eſtate, are like vnto <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> which may not bee touched; <note place="margin">Pſal. 125. 1.</note> but he that telleth them plainely of their faults, is counted preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; he that calleth a wateriſh ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>dropſie,</hi> or an angry humour the <hi>Gout,</hi> is thought now a daies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly, as though men were born to feed the humours of great ones: in reprouing men of inferiour ranck we ſhall finde reprehenſion like the flaying of a beaſt, the skinne goes from the body with much eaſe, and little labour; but when wee handle great men, wee ſhall finde reproofe ſticke at the head, and from thence the skinne of ſinne, as of a beaſt will
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2806:66"/> hardly be drawne. And this is the reaſon why great men are <hi>Veniſon</hi> in heauen, a rare diſh ſeldome ſeen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond Reproofe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I may alſo che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e another generation of people, who if they looke to their owne carriages, they reſpect not how others demeane themſelues. But are ready to ſay with <hi>Cain, Am I my brothers kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> And what haue I to doe with him? Let him looke to himſelfe if he will. Whereas S. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth vs <hi>to conſider or obſerue one another. And</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 24. Phil 2. 4. <hi>Id eſt, ea quae pertinent ad v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitatem a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>elm. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to looke not every man to his owne things, but every man alſo on the things of others;</hi> ſo farre forth as they concerne the good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of our brother. And ſo it falleth out often times, that wee are more beholding to our foes and enimies, then to our friends &amp; kindred, who pretend much loue to our perſons, but are too ſparing to our ſinnes; with them they will haue nothing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2806:66"/> to doe, or if they haue, it ſhall be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make and maintaine a vice to be a vertue; like the <hi>Fox</hi> in <hi>Aeſops Fables,</hi> who ſaid the <hi>Crow</hi> was a faire bird, and had a pleaſant note. Yea this want of reproofe may bee condemned much in <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> themſelues, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they ſhould exerciſe this good office vpon ſuch as haue relation to them, or they that are any way a gaine and profit to them; they can peradventure handle zealouſly the faults of inferiours, or it may be the inferiour faults of great ones; but if they ſhould light vpon that ſinne which chiefly liues and raignes in them, then they growe remiſſe and flacke handed, and rather ſooth vp the ſame with faire words and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered ſpeeches. Theſe are like the fierce <hi>Mastiue,</hi> that will barke and bay till his chaine cracke at a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and if he chance to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his reach, he will fly in the face of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2806:67"/> him: but if it be his maſter that hee ſees come, then his barking is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into fawning, becauſe he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his maſter vſeth to giue him cruſts and bones to feed on. Thus many will <hi>offend for a hit of bread;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ov. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> and for feare of a checke or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience from him that is reproued. And wee ſhall alſo finde that couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is a great cauſe of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as well as feare, becauſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it falleth out that men are made rich by the ſinnes of others, and this makes them like the <hi>Fox</hi> hunting after his prey, which wakes with his eyes ſhut; they ſee not, and yet ſee, they are wilfully blinde, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cloſed their eyes leaſt they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 28 27. Gen. 38. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould ſee;</hi> with <hi>Thamar,</hi> they muffle their eyes and will not ſee, and all becauſe the ſinnes of others bring advantage to them; I would this fault were not too commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the <hi>Courts</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> of the Land, who like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2806:67"/> 
                  <hi>Chirurgians</hi> keepe the wound raw, which they might ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably heale: and all for their own gaine and advantage. Yea I could wiſh that every man in his place would deale faithfully and plainely with the faults of others, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſearing the perſon or face of any man. I would men would condemne the ſinnes of others as plainely, as the <hi>Franciſcan Frier</hi> did <hi>Pope Sixtus</hi> the fourth, who came to be <hi>Pope</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame order. Who ſeeing the <hi>Frier,</hi> ſhewed him a great treaſure of mony, and ſaid vnto him. <hi>Frier,</hi> I cannot ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> did. <hi>Silver &amp; gold haue I none.</hi> No more can you ſay (ſaith the <hi>Frier)</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the man that was ſicke of the palſie, <hi>Ariſe and walke.</hi> If wee durſt thus behaue our ſelues, and that to the <note place="margin">Act. 3. 6.</note> greateſt, ſurely wee could not but bring forth ſome reformation from our good endeauours. And for our better encouragement, not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2806:68"/> with any, but to deale faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with all, let vs conſider the words of <hi>Solomon. Hee that ſaith to the wicked thou art righteous, him</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24. 24. 25</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall the people curſe, nations ſhall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre him. But to them that rebuke him ſhall be delight, and a good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhall come vpon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 5. Arguments to perſwade vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the ſinnes of others.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>First Argument the guilt of Sinne.</head>
                  <p>IF we reproue not ſin in others, <note place="margin">1 Argument to moue vs to reproue ſinne in others.</note> we make our ſelues guilty of the ſame ſinne, for the neglecting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny duty which is commanded, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth God as well as the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinnes prohibited, <hi>Curſe yee</hi>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:2806:68"/> 
                     <hi>Meroz, ſaith the Angell of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Indg. 5. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, curſe yee bitterly the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof;</hi> not becauſe they fought againſt the children of the Lord, but <hi>becauſe they did not aſsiſt the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> and we are as well liable to the curſe of God, for not helping the lord againſt ſin, as they that really tranſgreſſe the law; vice &amp; vertue are contraries which haue no medium, &amp; therefore <hi>in ſubiecto capaci,</hi> the abſence of the one muſt of neceſſity argue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the other, ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that hath authority to reproue ſin, is guilty of it, if he ſtrike it not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face with a ſeaſonable rebuke, and if a man neither lye nor ſweare himſelfe, yet if he ſuffer it in others; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ſinne is <note place="margin">Qui ferendi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>abet, ſolus in culpa eſt. ſi culpa non feritur B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. Amici vitia q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, facit ſua.</note> his owne, as in the <hi>Common wealth,</hi> and our lawes, the acceſſary is as well guiltie and lyable to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the principall: So in Gods <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> the not corrector as well as the law-breaker is both guilty of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2806:69"/> the ſinne and ſubiect to the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>For if a ſoule ſinne and heare</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Leuit. 5. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>the voice of ſwearing and is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whether hee hath ſeene or knowne of it, if he did not vtter it, then he ſhall beare his iniquity,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Lord</hi> admoniſheth <hi>the watchman to blow the trumpet, and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ezeck. 33. 7. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>warne the people from the Lord, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe if hee warned not the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man from his way, the wicked man ſhould dye in his iniquitie; but God would require his bloud at his handes.</hi> Now euery one in this caſe muſt be a watchman ouer his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to prohibit and rebuke ſinne in him; otherwiſe his brothers bloud ſhall be required at his handes. And thus it was in ancient times amongſt the Heathens themſelues; for the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> vſed to puniſh him that did not reproue the fault of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, with the ſame puniſhment that was due to the offender him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and thus wee ſee the ſinne of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2806:69"/> another man, by our ſilence may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our owne: and therefore the word <hi>mum</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> I take to be deriued from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>macula,</hi> a fault or blemiſh, ſo that in this kind to be mute or <hi>mum</hi> (as wee ſay) or to hold a mans tongue, is a ſinne and tranſgreſſion in the ſight of God; and certainely ſhall not goe vnpuniſhed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any man haue an eye to ſee ſinne, let him diſcouer it, if he haue an hand, let him plucke it vp; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe other mens ſinnes ſhall bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled amongſt ours, and ſo with <hi>Ely</hi> wee ſhall not only breake the necke of the body, but that of the <note place="margin">1. Sam. 4. 18.</note> ſoule alſo, and make the curſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans ſinnes light heauy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Second argument is charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſinner.</head>
                  <p>Secondly the duty of loue and <note place="margin">2 Argument to moue vsto reproue ſin.</note> charity wee owe one to another, bindes vs to this good office. In the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2806:70"/> old law we <hi>are commanded not to ſee</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>our neighbours oxe, nor his ſheepe to goe aſtray, and to hide our ſelues;</hi> but in any caſe to bring them againe vnto our brother, much more then are wee to reduce a ſtraying ſoule into the waies of God, and good reaſon, for wee are all of vs fellow members of that body whereof <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> is the head, now we know members of a body are helpefull to one another; if the foot haue a thorne in it, the head ſtoopes, &amp; the handes helpe to pluck it out againe. We are brethren as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>Brethren if any one bee ouertaken in</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>a fault, &amp;c.</hi> fraternall and brotherly affection muſt be a ſpurre to pricke vs on to ſhew our loue in this action which indeed is a ſure tryall &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of the beſt loue, and on <note place="margin">Probatio dilect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ionis eſt exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio operis Greg. Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ia q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> illum quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>endo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>radit Diabolo.</note> the contrary it's a curſed friendſhip and aſſociation which by a wicked taciturnitie and conniuence at finne giues vp the ſoule of the ſinner into
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2806:70"/> the handes of the <hi>Diuell.</hi> Therefore in this kinde it is good wee ſhould deale as one louing friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who beholding him dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and deepely affected with ſome diſeaſe or ſickneſſe, hee will carefully prouide the <hi>Chirurgion</hi> or <hi>Phyſition</hi> for his cure and reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his former health: thus let vs ſtriue to haue as much ſpirituall loue as moſt men haue naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that when wee ſee our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euill affected with ſinne, which is the ſickneſſe of the ſoule, wee may by wiſe and ſeaſonable rebukes make vp and heale the ſores and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> batteries of ſinne and Satan, in the hearts of our brethren. The good <hi>Samaritan</hi> that found the maimed man in miſerie, that was <hi>fallen amongſt theeues, had compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 33. 34.</note> 
                     <hi>on him, and bound vp his wounds:</hi> ſhall not wee then much more haue compaſſion vpon a Brother, when wee ſee him lye vnder the hands of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2806:71"/> his ſpirituall enimies, and bind vp the wounds of his ſoule, by holy &amp; Godly rebukes? Hauing reaſon from the law of equitie and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ience more to commiſerate the diſeaſes of the ſoule, then of the body. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>withhold not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 13. 14</note> 
                     <hi>correction from the child, for if thou beateſt him with the rod, he ſhall not dye; thou ſhalt beat him with the rod, and ſhalt deliuer his ſoule from hell.</hi> Thus if wee withhold not a ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rebuke when wee ſee our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne, we may happily deliuer his ſoule from death &amp; Satan, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reproofe is called the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life, becauſe it tendeth and lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to life. <hi>The eare that heareth the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 31. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>reproofe of life</hi> abideth among the wiſe: let vs try therefore, if by this meanes wee can conuert a man that is erring from the truth, and we ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhall <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is audie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> increpationem vitarum.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. 5. 19. 20. Mat. 18. 15.</note> hide a multitude of ſinnes. I might fairely launch forth, and with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2806:71"/> gale, ſet vp ſaile, and away into an Ocean of reaſons, or argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to moue vs to this duty: as the honour of God, or the enſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſinner and the ſtanders by, who by our ſilence, may halfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues, a ſinne to be no ſinne; or elſe ſo ſmall as not worthy a reprehenſion, or that wee are ſuch as they are, and loue the ſinne if wee reproue it not, alſo by our reproofe <note place="margin">
                        <hi>See M. Bolton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> direction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> for walking with, God. pag.</hi> 122. <hi>ſine.</hi>
                     </note> wee may keepe out the infection &amp; contagion of ſinne whereby our ſoules may bee poyſoned, but for breuities ſake, I will leaue them to the iudgement and amplification of the reader, and him and them to the bleſſing of that holy ſpirit, who giu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth grace to the reprouer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, both how to ſpeake, and how to take a word of reproofe in due ſeaſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
